<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Unrighteousness no plea for truth, nor ignorance a lover of it. Being an answer to a book called A plea for truth, in love to truth, subscribed by James Pope, wherein is contained his answer to several queries (sent to him by Thomas White) which are tried and found unsatisfactory, and James Popes Ten queries to the people (called) Quakers fully answered. : Also the doctrine and practise of the people (called Baptists) ... With a full discussion of their principles ... / By a true lover of all their souls and eternal welfare. John Crook.</title>
            <author>Crook, John, 1617-1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 146 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81048</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7225A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R171617</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45789264</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45789264</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172575</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81048)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172575)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2639:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Unrighteousness no plea for truth, nor ignorance a lover of it. Being an answer to a book called A plea for truth, in love to truth, subscribed by James Pope, wherein is contained his answer to several queries (sent to him by Thomas White) which are tried and found unsatisfactory, and James Popes Ten queries to the people (called) Quakers fully answered. : Also the doctrine and practise of the people (called Baptists) ... With a full discussion of their principles ... / By a true lover of all their souls and eternal welfare. John Crook.</title>
                  <author>Crook, John, 1617-1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher> Printed for Tho. Simmons at the Bull &amp; Mouth near Aldersgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Friends' Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Pope, James.</term>
               <term>White, Thomas.</term>
               <term>Baptists --  England --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172575:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Unrighteouſneſs NO PLEA FOR TRUTH, Nor Ignorance a Lover of it.</p>
            <p>Being an Anſwer to a book called <hi>A Plea for Truth, in love to Truth,</hi> ſubſcribed by <hi>James Pope,</hi> Wherein is contained his Anſwer to ſeveral Queries (ſent to him by <hi>Thomas White</hi>) which are tried and found unſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory, and <hi>James Popes Ten Queries</hi> to the people (called) Quakers fully anſwered.</p>
            <p>Alſo the Doctrine and Practiſe of the People (called Baptiſts) examined and weighed (in the true ballance) and found too light,</p>
            <p>With a full diſcuſſion of their Principles, and particularly their Ordinances of breaking bread and water-baptiſm, &amp;c. With ſome Queries to all the People called Baptiſts (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they are to be found) for them to anſwer in Truth and Righteouſneſſe, and in Gods fear.</p>
            <p>By a true Lover of all their ſouls and eternal welfare. <hi>JOHN CROOK.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Try all things, and hold faſt that which is good.</p>
               <p>For enquire, I pray thee, of the former age, and prepare thy ſelfe to the ſearch of their fathers
<bibl>
                     <hi>Job 8.8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>He ſhall lean upon his houſe, but it ſhall not ſtand; he ſhall hold it faſt, but it ſhall not endure,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Job 8.15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Tho. Simmons</hi> at the <hi>Bull</hi> &amp; <hi>Mouth</hi> near <hi>Alderſgate,</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:172575:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:172575:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Lord of Hoſts is ariſen and ariſing in his power to ſhake the earth, and not onely the Earth but Heaven alſo, that that which cannot be ſhaken may remain; and this ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king is for the removing of thoſe things which are ſhaken, as of things that are made; And for Alaruming of the World, and awakening all profeſſions and Profeſſors, that ſo every man may betake himſelf to his God, and he that anſwers by fire, and conſumes the chaffe and ſtubble, let him be God, and all bow before him, that ſo his Name may be exalted above every name, and that to him every knee may bow, both of things in Heaven and things in Earth, for to him muſt all bow and bend; and the Prophet which he hath raiſed up must all hear or be cut off from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people; and this Prophet is like unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> and muſt go before <hi>Iſrael</hi> to lead the holy Seed out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and to divide the Sea for <hi>Iſrael</hi> to paſſe, and to ſtand in the gap to intercede, that ſo the Lords wrath may be appeaſed; but they that refuſe him that ſpeaks cannot eſcape; Therefore Reader whoſoever thou art, take heed that thou neglect not this the day of thy viſitation, nor that great ſalvation which is proffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to thee in the light of Christ, for if thou harden thy heart againſt it, thou cannot proſper, (neither canſt thou ever hear his voyce, nor ſee his ſhape, but in the light) for he will not alwayes ſtrive with thee, neither will he accept an offering at
<pb facs="tcp:172575:3"/>thy hand, while thou rebels againſt his light that ſhines in thy heart, to give thee the knowledge of God in Chriſt; for Gods ſoul is weary of all vain oblations that are offered up in the wills of men, and of their humility that is feigned, and of al their Aſſemblies though they multiply them, while obedience and hearkening to his voyce (in the conſcience) is not regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Therefore turn ye, turn ye to the true light, that with it you may ſee your ſelves, and from that ſight receive the ſentence of death upon your ſelves, that you may not truſt in your ſelves, but in the living God, that ſo every one of you may know by experience that by grace you are ſaved, not of your ſelves, but by the free gift, and this free gift may lead and guide you in all your Worſhip, that ſo ſelf may have no ſhare in it, but every one of you may be juſtified before the Lord both in your ſayings and doings, that you may be able to endure ſound Doctrine, which ſearches the heart and tryes the reins, and keeps low, waiting for the fulfilling of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe viz. <hi>(That all the people of the Lord ſhall be taught of the Lord)</hi> &amp; may not heap up teachers to your ſelves to pleaſe the itching ear. And what thou meeteſt with in this diſcourſe that may ſeem ſharp or piercing, take it as the ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a friend, not given to hurt the life, but to wound that nature and birth which muſt not be heir with the free-born, but must be cast out, or elſe to the Inheritance of the Saints in light thou canſt not come, nor into the holy City thou canſt not enter (which hath been trodden under foot) though thou may dwell in the outward courts, for that must be given to the Gentiles. Therefore haſt, haſt, haſt and come out (leaſt being partaker of the ſin, thou be partaker of the plague alſo) and meet the Lord while he is nigh, and call upon him while he may be found, leaſt the door be ſhut, and there be no en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance for thee.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:172575:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>JAMES POPE,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving ſeen a Paper with thy name ſubſcribed to it, in anſwer to a Paper of <hi>Thomas Whites,</hi> directed to the People called Baptiſts) which thou calls <hi>A Plea for Truth in love to Truth,</hi> which Title agreeth not with thy Book, if thou intendeſt the writing following thy Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Page, and ſo on to the end of the Book.</p>
            <p>For in the third line of thy Book, I finde a ſaying which is none of Truths Plea, which is the cauſe and inducement that moved thee to write thy following diſcourſe, in theſe words, <hi>It hath moved me to write this following anſwer, becauſe none elſe (that thou knoweſt of) hath done it:</hi> What thou meaneſt (<hi>by it hath moved thee)</hi> I do not underſtand, becauſe thou haſt given two Reaſons of thy writing of thy Book; one is becauſe thou ſayeſt thou <hi>art one of thoſe people to whom</hi> Tho. White <hi>directed his Paper,</hi> and thy ſecond Reaſon ſeems to be becauſe <hi>thou hadſt two of thoſe Papers given to thee,</hi> and then ſaith, It hath moved thee to write this following Anſwer, &amp;c. This ſavors more of the voice of a ſtranger then to be Truths Plea; If by <hi>it</hi> thou in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeſt the Spirit of God, why didſt thou not name it? Or doſt thou queſtion its Authority, as not being ſufficient of it ſelf without ſome other motive? or doſt thou not intend that at all, as not believing it neceſſary to ſuch a work, or as not being thy rule to walk by? or waſt thou (when thou began to write thy Book) as one ſurprized with fear, ſpeaking that which thou underſtood not thy ſelf, and ſo let it paſs, as hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it might meet with the ſame acceptance from the Reader, being cloathed with this beautiful Title of <hi>A Plea for truth in love to Truth,</hi> and then begins thy Book thus; <hi>Foraſmuch as I am one of thoſe people to whom</hi> Thomas White <hi>hath directed his Paper, and having two of thoſe Papers given to me, it hath moved me to write this following Anſwer, becauſe none elſe (that I know of) hath done it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>James Pope,</hi> I may juſtly ſuſpect to find more of thy Pleas to be none of Truths, neither come they from Truth, nor tend they to the Honour of Truth, onely thou makes uſe of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:172575:4"/>Name Truth as a Superſcription or image upon thy counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit Coin to make it paſs for currant, but being uſed to ſuch Coin (from ſuch hands) makes me the more jealous; and had thou not uſed the word Truth ſo much I might not have been ſo ſtrict in my examination, but in the true Ballance are thy words weighed, and they are found too light, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned as nothing ſound, and ſo no Plea for Truth, nor ſpoken in Love to Truth, but to hide ſome beloved Image which thou cal's Truth, and would have others to take it ſo to be, but though they may be <hi>Jacobs</hi> words, yet they are <hi>Eſaus</hi> hands, and the bleſſing he muſt not have; and ſo thou haſt not named thy Book right.</p>
            <p>Then thou ſayeſt, <hi>I appeal to all unbyaſed men and women in the World, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>James Pope,</hi> Thy appeal is too large for a buſineſs of no more concernment, it may be determined by a leſſe compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and that in Righteouſneſs too, and yet judgement may be given againſt thee, both for thy raſh appeal and haſty charge againſt <hi>Thomas White</hi> in ſaying, <hi>ſhooting this his firſt Fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Dart;</hi> if it hath wounded, it is becauſe the Armour of Light was not put on, for it was not ſhot at a Friend but at an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, neither was it a Fiery Dart ſhot toward the Life, but to ſtick faſt in the Liver of the Man of Sin, that that which is of God may go free, and the exalted and the mighty be thrown from his Seat. And whereas thou ſayeſt, either he knows thoſe of the Baptiſts, or he knows them not that ſtumble at and contend againſt Chriſt. <hi>Thomas White</hi> doth not charge all the Baptiſts with ſtumbling at and contending againſt that in which alone all worſhip, prayers, ſacrifices are accepted in the ſight of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> neither doth he call them contenders againſt Chriſt (in thoſe words) but if thou had been indued with patience throughly, thou might have read this word (therefore) or reaſon of his ſo ſpeaking to the Baptiſts, which is that except their worſhip, prayers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> do come from a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of him (in you) who is the light of the World, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> you are but warming your ſelves at your own ſparks; but of thoſe words thou takeſt no notice, either as not knowing a meaſure of him who is the Light of the world to be in thee, or elſe doſt not believe that there is a meaſure of God in man firſt to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:172575:4"/>be known before God himſelf in his fulnes come to be known; and there is the drawings of the Father firſt to be known be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt be come unto, and there is the forming of Chriſt in man before Chriſt be born and brought forth, 1 <hi>John</hi> 6.44. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.19. But thou overlooking of the meaſure of Chriſt in thee, in thy reading of his Book, ſpeaks thee guilty of overlooking the meaſure of Light given to thee to profit withal, and ſo wouldſt be dealing by whole-ſale, before thou knoweſt Chriſt formed in thee, and ſomething that is pure in thy own heart to guide thee, given thee freely of God to lead thee into Truth, which is more then into words that are true. And ſo thy ſaying that the People <hi>Thomas White</hi> writes unto <hi>do know all ſacrifices are onely accepted in Chriſt,</hi> ſeems to be too haſty a confeſſion, and to be too much like the People of <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> of old ſpoken of, <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.28, 29. I have heard the voice of the words of this people, which they have ſpoken unto thee, they have well ſaid all that they have ſpoken. O that there were ſuch an heart in them; and like the fooliſh virgins whoſe lamps were gone out, and yet kept their confidence Lord, Lord open to us; and like to <hi>Nicodemus</hi> confeſſion who readily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to Chriſt, but knew not the Kingdom in him like a grain of Muſtard-ſeed, no more then the <hi>Phariſees.</hi> And therefore <hi>James Pope,</hi> ſearch and try thy ſelf whether thou haſt any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proof of all <hi>Sacrifices being accepted in Chriſt,</hi> then that 1 <hi>Peter</hi> and that of <hi>Epheſians</hi> 1. if not, what proof haſt thou more then all Engliſh-men have, and yet all Engliſh-men do not know Chriſt in them, nor that all is accepted in Chriſt, though they have read it ſo, as well as thou, but are offering up both ſtrange fleſh and ſtrange fire. And therefore be not angry, nor call it a reviling ſlander, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Thomas White</hi> ſaid many <hi>Baptiſts</hi> are profeſſing, preaching, praying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and yet ſtumbling at and contending againſt that in which all worſhip is accepted in the ſight of God, for this is and may be true, and therefore no ſuch Fiery Dart as thou wouldeſt repreſent it to be, nor no <hi>reviling ſlander,</hi> nor is he to be <hi>reproved for ſpeaking evil of things he knows not;</hi> and therefore thy thoughts that <hi>he ought to be deeply humbled before the Lord for this,</hi> are as vain and unſound as thy miſtake was, in what moved thee to write thy Book; for may not <hi>Thomas
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172575:5"/>White</hi> know many <hi>Baptiſts</hi> that <hi>have ſtumbled at and contended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the light of Chriſt which every man that cometh into the World is lighted with?</hi> are not many ſuch known at this day in <hi>England?</hi> nay, doſt not thou and others know many who are called Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts that diſpute againſt the light and grace of God given to all men, as being ſufficient to lead to ſalvation, and deny that which checks and reproves for ſin in men and women, to be the ſaving light of Chriſt? now do not ſuch who thus ſay, and thus believe, ſtumble at, &amp; contend againſt that in which alone all worſhip is accepted in Gods ſight? and beſides is <hi>T. White</hi> any more an offender for not naming thoſe particular Baptiſts that do ſo ſtumble and diſpute, then <hi>Paul</hi> was blamable for not naming thoſe amongſt the <hi>Corinthians</hi> that he charged with eating diſorderly, or thoſe that he charges with being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equally yoked, or then thoſe he charges with being ſick and weak, for the cauſes mentioned in his <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> and yet names not the perſons? no more doth it follow that either <hi>Thomas White</hi> doth not know ſuch as he charges, or elſe he was bound to name them, or otherwiſe he muſt be taxed for being <hi>no friend to the ſouls of all the Baptiſts,</hi> or <hi>for ſhooting of fiery darts againſt them,</hi> or <hi>for being a reviling ſlanderer, and ought deeply to be humbled for the ſame;</hi> but <hi>James Pope,</hi> thou doſt not divide aright thy Exhortations, but art an unskilful Preacher, for this <hi>deep humiliation</hi> belongs to thy ſelf both for thy ignorance and for thy hypocriſie, in covering over thy unadviſed ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with the painted garment of <hi>a plea for truth,</hi> when truth doth not own thy words; for let but the wiſe in heart judge and they will ſee, that thy hard, ignorant, and raſh charges are as ſtrong againſt <hi>Paul</hi> (upon the reaſons alledged) as againſt <hi>Thomas White;</hi> but they will fall upon thy own pate; and upon a ſerious ſearch of thy heart in Gods fear and light, my ſayings may be of cloſer and nearer concernment to thy ſelf and many of thy brethren then thou art at preſent ſenſible of, but if repentance prevent not (in time) thou mayeſt feel the weight.</p>
            <p>In thy 2. page, thou ſaiſt, <hi>That thou doſt wiſh that</hi> Thomas White <hi>and his friends may alſo carefully walk by the rule</hi> T.W. <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth to thee and thy friends; then thou ſaiſt, he will be ſo far from ſpeaking againſt his holy appointments, that he will love and keep
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:172575:5"/>them;</hi> maiſt thou not be judged out of thy own mouth? Did <hi>Thomas White</hi> ſhoot a fiery dart? and doſt thou not ſhoot a poiſoned arrow? and doſt not thou charge him with ſpeaking againſt Gods holy appointments, and as if he neither loved them, nor kept them, nor delighted in thoſe that did? How many falſities and untruths are here in two lines? was it no better then a <hi>reviling ſlander in Thomas White,</hi> and didſt thou judge it ſo, and therefore ſaith <hi>that thou thinkeſt that he ought to be deeply humbled before the Lord for the ſame,</hi> becauſe he ſaid, <hi>while many of you are profeſſing, praying and yet ſtumbling at, &amp; contending againſt that in which alone all worſhip</hi> &amp;c. <hi>is accepted in the ſight of God?</hi> Is his offence ſo great becauſe he did not name them, though he knew them? and is thy offence mitigated, becauſe thou names <hi>Thomas White,</hi> but chargeſt him falſely with that which thou canſt not prove againſt him, and yet calls thy ſayings, <hi>a plea for truth</hi> &amp;c? as if thy Title to thy Book were to priviledge thy calumnies, and Authority ſufficient to paſs thy reproaches without a review or farther examination; but thy beautiful Title is but like the Phariſees beautifying the outſide of the cup and platter while the inſide was foul, and like Pilate, who wrote a good Title over Chriſt calling him King of the <hi>Jews,</hi> but delivered him up to be crucified as a blaſphemer; So thy fair Title doth but aggravate thy offence, in that thou ſlanders the innocent, and calls it <hi>a plea for truth, in love to truth,</hi> as if light and darkneſs could unite together, and truth and falſhood marry each other, which neither can be, neither ſhall they go unpuniſhed who go about to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile them.</p>
            <p>In the 3. <hi>page</hi> of thy Book, thou askeſt <hi>Thomas White</hi> in thoſe words, <hi>why doſt thou upbraid us? do we ſay that the Scriptures direct not to, or ſpeak not of a light within? we both know and ſay that the Scripture ſaith</hi> 2 Cor. 4.6. <hi>that God hath ſhined in the hearts of his Saints, to give the light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Chriſt. James Pope,</hi> when thou ſaiſt, <hi>do we ſay,</hi> and <hi>we both know and ſay,</hi> &amp;c. Doſt thou onely intend thy ſelf, and ſome one or two more, or doſt thou intend all the Baptiſts generally? ſeeing that thy ſelf may not be ignorant how many Baptiſts have both in Print and diſputes publikely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owned the light within that checks and reproves for ſin to be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:172575:6"/>ſufficient to lead to ſalvation, which thou ſeems to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in words to be true, and chargeſt <hi>Thomas White</hi> for up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braiding of you, in that he ſaith, are not many of you ſtrangers to the light, whilſt you are queſtioning whether the Scriptures declare of, or direct to a light within &amp;c. which thing hath often been queſtioned by many Baptiſts, and ſuch as are none of the leaſt in eſteem among you, and if thou wilt declare againſt them that have ſo queſtioned and diſputed, and deny fellowſhip with them, for not being ſound in the faith, I may help thee to a Catalogue of their names, the publike diſpute at <hi>Dunſtable</hi> may bring ſome of them to thy remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance; But are you not better informed then you were ſome years ſince, and ſomewhat rectified in your judgements? if ſo, let the praiſe be given to God, and your former errours and miſtakes be printed and publiſhed for others to take heed by, eſpecially ſeeing many who are called Baptiſts in <hi>England</hi> are yet in the dark and queſtioning what thou, on the behalf of thy brethren, ſeems to confeſſe to, and let your unity make it appear that you do not onely confeſſe to the light within (that checks and reproves for ſin, to be that alone which gives the knowledge of God in the face of Chriſt, and that a man cannot have the knowledge of God in Chriſt, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the light give it to him) but alſo that you walk in the light, and have fellowſhip one with another in the light, and that in it you witneſs the blood of Jeſus Chriſt to cleanſe you from all ſin; that ſo none of you may ſtumble at the Doctrine of perfection: but if you ſay, you have fellowſhip with God, and are in the fellowſhip of the Goſpel, and walk in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſtumble at figures and ſhadows, you lie, and do not the truth, for in him is no darkneſs at all.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou ſayeſt, Thomas White <hi>deals uncharitably with you in putting you in the number of thoſe that are loſt, in whom the God of this world hath blinded their eyes,</hi> &amp;c. It is no unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tableneſs to ſpeak the truth; and to ſay that thoſe who are ſtumbling at that (which is given them to lead out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) are ſuch as the God of this world hath blinded their minds; and that ſuch are in a loſt eſtate, and the Goſpel of their ſalvation they do not know, for it is hid from them, and he that judges ſuch ſo to be, is not uncharitable, but
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172575:6"/>his judgement is juſt, and the uncharitableneſs doth light upon thy own head.</p>
            <p>And whereas, thou ſayeſt in theſe words, <hi>thou muſt give me leave to query how thou dareſt abuſe us,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>James,</hi> thy tongue is too much thy own in ſpeaking leeſing, for leave I do not give thee to query of that which is not, for that is breath ſpent in vain, for it is no abuſe to query how they can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe they <hi>know God, who deny the light of his Son within,</hi> but leaves out theſe following words, <hi>viz. in which the Father is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, and by which that that may be known of God is made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in man,</hi> is this a plea for truth, in love to truth, to take half a ſentence, or ſo much as may ſerve to make a cavil, and leave out that which is the main and explanatory part of the whole? or is it rather in imitation of him who made uſe of Scripture to tempt Chriſt withal, but left out what might make againſt his deſign? may he not juſtly be charged as a tranſgreſſor that ſhall ſay there is no God, though he quote the Scripture for it, which ſaith, there is no God, but leaves out the foregoing words which makes the ſaying true, which is that the fool hath ſaid in his heart there is no God? doth thy crime differ in any thing from his that ſhould ſo ſay more then this that he leave out the foregoing words, and thou leaves out <hi>Thomas Whites</hi> following words? and to ſay that ſuch a one is a deceitful worker, and for it muſt come to judgement, is but to ſpeak truth plainly, and therefore take <hi>Thomas Whites</hi> words at length as they are in his Book, and may it not juſtly be queried, <hi>how can thoſe Baptiſts profeſſe they know God, whilſt they are denying the light of his Son within, in which the Father is revealed, and by which that which may be known of God is made manifeſt in man?</hi> ſeeing ſuch hath appeared in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to this light, both by publike Printing and diſputing, and if thou <hi>James Pope</hi> do not own them to be of you, declare it publikely, that ſo they may come to repentance, and you be clear of their blood.</p>
            <p>And whereas, thou ſayeſt, <hi>the Lord in mercy hath made you to own him to be your life and light, who alſo is leading you in the way to that light which is unapproachable,</hi> &amp;c. I cannot but take notice of thy confuſion, who ſpeaks like one that hath got a thing by
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172575:7"/>rote, but underſtandeſt not what thou ſayeſt; for is <hi>Chriſt your very light and life who is leading of you in the way to that light which is unapproachable,</hi> and is not that ſame Chriſt that is the light and life, alſo the way, and the light which is unap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachable, or is there one Chriſt that is the very life and light, and leader in the way and approachable, and another Chriſt that is the way, &amp; that light which is unapproachable; if thou kneweſt what thou ſaid, thou would know that the very life and light is unapproachable; but doſt thou not in thoſe words manifeſt thy ignorance of Gods Chriſt the way to the Father, and light of the world, and life of men, and by thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention haſt found out one Chriſt to be thy very light and life, and is leading of thee in the way to another Chriſt which is unapproachable; ſo that to one Chriſt thou art already come, who is thy light and life, and he is leading of thee in the way to that light which is unapproachable; by this thou mayeſt ſee where thou art, for in the world are Gods many, and Lords many, but to us there is but one God and one Lord Jeſus, and we know that an Idol is nothing, howbeit there is not in all men this knowledge.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou ſpeaks of holy appointments and Chriſts Ordinances, and who ever denyes them, they are they which deny the light, &amp;c. Thou ſhouldſt ſpeak plainly what thoſe appointments are that thou intendeſt, becauſe you Baptiſts differ ſo much among your ſelves about them; one ſaith Chriſt hath appointed hands to be laid on, and another ſaith Chriſt hath appointed the waſhing of the Diſciples feet, and another ſaith anointing with oil is an Ordinance, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaith good chear or love feaſts before the ſupper is an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, and ſome ſay ſprinkling is enough, others ſay they muſt be dipped over head and ears; and ſome ſay the bread muſt be cut, others that it muſt be broken, ſome ſay it muſt be taken and broken by him that eats it, others ſay it muſt be broken before hand and given them by an officer of the Church; and ſome ſay ſinging is an Ordinance, and others ſay no, and many other things which Baptiſts call Ordinances and appointments, but which are thine, or thoſe that thou calls Chriſts appointments and Inſtitutions thou haſt not yet declared thy ſelf; ſeeing all theſe are called Chriſts appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and ordinances by thoſe who plead for them; but I
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172575:7"/>ſhould counſel thee, firſt to be reconciled to thy brethren, and agree with them which be Chriſts appointments, and which be mens inventions, or mens miſunderſtanding of Chriſts words; and then I may declare to thee which are to continue, and which are at an end, the ſubſtance being come; until then take heed thou deal not with his Ordinances as thou haſt dealt with his Name, in calling that a plea for truth, in love to truth, which indeed is but a cover for deceit. And you that are called Baptiſts above ſome others make it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt your fellowſhip is not in the light, becauſe you have not fellowſhip one with another, and therefore though you confeſs to the light, yet I may ſay thou walks not in the light, while thou imagines two Chriſts, <hi>one to be the very life and light,</hi> and the other to be <hi>a light unapproachable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas thou grants that it was <hi>the end of the Apoſtles Miniſtry, to turn people from darkneſs to light;</hi> and grants <hi>that many at this day tramples under foot the Son of God,</hi> &amp;c. and I doubt not but all in his book (that thou haſt not anſwered) thou grants; and touching <hi>the Doctrine of Election and Reprobation,</hi> thou ſaiſt, that <hi>the people which</hi> Tho. White <hi>writes to, do differ in their underſtandings of it, and therefore ſhall paſs it by,</hi> &amp;c. Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>James</hi> thou grants ſo much, and paſſeſt by ſuch things, that now I do not wonder thou underſtood not what it was that moved thee to write thy book (except to ſee thy name in Print) Art thou aſhamed <hi>of thy Doctrine of Election and Reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> how wilt thou avoid the cenſure of Chriſt? ſaying, <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever denies me before men, him will I alſo deny before my Father which is in Heaven,</hi> Mat. 10.33. <hi>And if we deny him, he alſo will deny us,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.12. And if you that are Baptiſts do differ in ſuch a fundamental thing as Election and Reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, how can ye be in the Faith or fellowſhip of the Goſpel, ſeeing it is the Election that obtains, and the Reprobation that enters not? And if you differ in your underſtandings about this, how can you underſtand any thing aright, ſeeing no Faith but the Faith of Gods Elect is ſound and good, nor no Salvation can be witneſſed, until Calling and Election be not onely known, but made ſure? and yet the Baptiſts differ in your underſtandings about it; And therefore muſt ye needs be at a loſs, and in an uncertain ſtate, as to your eternal wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare and happineſs, and alwayes lyable to be deceived, for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172575:8"/>it is onely the Elect that are impoſſible to be deceived; and therefore no marvel why you are ſo devided and deceived, ſeeing you differ in your underſtandings about Election. Haſt, haſt, haſt unto the light of Chriſt that ſhines in your dark hearts, that that may give you the underſtanding of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection and Reprobation;</hi> for now it is evident that while thou and others are differing about Election, and know it not, your Religion is in vain; and Chriſt the light you do not know, and therefore no marvel thou ſpeaks of one Chriſt <hi>that is thy light and life,</hi> and another <hi>light that is unapproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In thy fourth page thou ſeems to be diſpleaſed with <hi>Thomas White</hi> for cautioning of thee <hi>to take heed of deceit,</hi> &amp;c. Is it not time to caution thee and others to take heed of deceit, ſeeing you differ in your underſtanding about Election, and none are out of a poſſibility of being deceived but the Elect, and you and others differing in your underſtandings about it, is it not time to cry to you Baptiſts above others, <hi>take beed of being deceived?</hi> Yea, take heed you are not deceived in your Ordinan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, in your Church fellowſhip, yea, and in your Chriſt too, ſeeing one Chriſt <hi>is your very light and life, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther light that is unapproachable is he leading you in the way to.</hi> And be not angry, becauſe <hi>Thomas White</hi> exhorts you to look to your building, leaſt it be pulled down to your loſs, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther call it judging of the hearts of Gods people any more, ſeeing thou haſt made thy heart, and what is in it ſo manifeſt. And <hi>for thoſe Invectives which thou ſaiſt are ſo frequent in our papers,</hi> thou ſhouldeſt have named ſome of them, and who were their Authours, otherwiſe now canſt thou expect an anſwer? but doth not fear ſurprize the hypocrite, and are not the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites in <hi>Sion</hi> afraid, and cry out do not judge leaſt you be judged, not knowing to whom that was ſpoken? <hi>Luke</hi> 6.37. to whom he ſpake a parable and ſaid, <hi>Can the blind lead the blind? ſhall they not both fall into the ditch?</hi> The blind are forbidden to judge, but not the ſpiritual man, who judgeth all things, nor he whoſe eyes are opened to ſee good and evil; and he that judgeth any thing in another, that he hath not firſt judged in himſelf, is a tranſgreſſor; but he that judges that in another which hath been firſt judged in himſelf, is no mans enemy, though in the time of mans love to his luſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:172575:8"/>he may count him his enemy, becauſe he tells him the truth; but when he comes to be awakened, he will count him his brother, becauſe he would not ſuffer ſin to lye upon him, nor the Sun to go down in his wrath.</p>
            <p>And thou ſaiſt, <hi>That which you call Church-fellowſhip, you do not miſcal it, for it is true Church-fellowſhip according to the Order of our bleſsed Lord Jeſus, which he himſelf hath inſtituted, and his holy Apoſtles and Primitive Saints practiſed, in which fellowſhip (though contemned by you) do we walk ſweetly together, having his preſence with us, and his bleſſing upon us,</hi> &amp;c. And many other words thou uſeth and applieth to thy ſelf and brethren, which are the words of others, and the conditions of others, and thou applieſt them to thy ſelf and thy brethren; thou ſhouldeſt firſt have proved thy ſelf and brethren born of the ſame ſpirit that they were, and led into thoſe things (in which they wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked) by the ſame ſpirit that they were, and not in the imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without the ſame command that they had, and leading which they were well acquainted withal as many as were the ſons of God, for they ſpake as they were moved by the Spirit, and in it did they worſhip, and by it were they guided to know when to go and when to ſtand ſtill, and by it they knew well their own ſpirits, &amp; when ſelf ſpake at any time, and in it had they fellowſhip together, and by the ſame Rule did they walk according to their ſeveral attainments; but were not of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sects, neither did they cry up their own inventions for Chriſts Commands, neither did thy differ about what were his appointments, ſome crying one thing, and ſome another, like <hi>Babylons</hi> builders, inſomuch that their languages are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, and they cannot underſtand one another, what was the Primitive Order, and what are now thoſe appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments believers are to be found Practitioners of; But one cryes this, and another that, but all in errour from the Spirit of the Lord, who knows not the movings of his Spirit in them, nor knows not that Chriſt the Leader, and Chriſt the Way, and Chriſt that dwells in the light unapproachable, and is the light of the world, all is but one Chriſt; neither knows E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection nor Reprobation, but differs in their underſtandings about them; all ſuch are out of the Appointments and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of Chriſt, and as yet knows not the Way of his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:172575:9"/>as it was performed in the dayes of the Apoſtles; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſay not Chriſts <hi>Inſtitutions are contemned,</hi> becauſe mens Traditions and carnal Imitations are not followed, all which muſt tumble down, when <hi>Babylon</hi> the great the Mother of Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots falls; and when that comes to paſs, it will be no wonder to thoſe that behold her downfal, that are come out of her, to ſee many pleaſant Pictures ſpoiled, and lofty Cities laid low, and Maſter builders (that have rejected the light) bewailing the fall of their Towers, which they thought had been ſo high, and built upon ſuch a foundation as could not be ſhaken, and of ſuch materials as they thought had been living ſtones, and formed in all things like the Primitive Churches; but their attire will be found to be the attire of the Harlot, and not of the true Spouſe, neither her comeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that which Chriſt hath put upon her, but a <hi>paint</hi> like <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabel,</hi> and a <hi>Harlot,</hi> though <hi>welfavoured;</hi> and though her gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be purple and ſcarlet-coloured, yet not waſhed with the blood of the Lamb, and therefore follows him not whereſoever he goeth. And whereas thou ſaiſt, <hi>you walk ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly together;</hi> How can that be, ſeeing you differ in ſo many things, and main things too, as <hi>Election</hi> and <hi>Reprobation?</hi> For how can two walk together, except they be agreed? and yet thou confeſſes you walk ſweetly together, and alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes you are not agreed in <hi>Election,</hi> &amp;c. Therefore may I not ſay there is no light in thee, becauſe thou walks not according to this Rule, which ſaith, <hi>Can two walk together, except they be agreed?</hi> Amos 3.3.</p>
            <p>Thouſaiſt, <hi>Thomas White</hi> is deceived in that he cautions you of being deceived your ſelves, while you cry out others are deluded; you who are joyned in that which you call fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, by the outward form (of waſhing, &amp;c.) Is not the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake on thy own part? Are you not ſo joyned? If thou canſt plead not guilty, who elſe can, ſeeing thou ſeems to juſtifie all that are called Baptiſts? For <hi>Tho. Whites</hi> paper is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected in general to thoſe people called Baptiſts, and what is both ſpoken in general, and to ſome in particular, thou ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies to thy ſelf and brethren as either being guilty of all, or elſe taking thy ſelf to be united to all that are dipped in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and ſo by the tendency of thy diſcourſe, thou pleads
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:172575:9"/>for all the people called Baptiſts (though they be ſuch as differ from thee in the underſtanding of the great buſineſs of <hi>Election and Reprobation</hi>) as if thou wert eſpecially concerned in that name; though there be many others who are not ſo called, and yet do not differ in ſuch weighty matters from thee and thy brethren, as many of thoſe people who are called Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts do, all which being put together ſpels little leſs, then that you are joyned in your fellowſhip by your outward form of waſhing; becauſe thou pleads for, and takes thy ſelf to be eſpecially concerned in all things charged againſt the waſhed, or baptiſts, which imports no leſs then that you are joyned in your fellowſhip by outward waſhing, otherwiſe why doſt thou not deny ſome of thoſe people called Baptiſts, ſeeing by your own confeſſion you differ in your underſtanding, and that underſtanding which differs from truth is not good, and ſo none of Gods gift, and ſuch, what they know they know naturally like bruit beaſts, and how canſt thou have fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with them, except it be becauſe you are both outwardly waſhed, and ſo are joyned together in fellowſhip by that out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward form, in other things having no fellowſhip. And ſo <hi>James Pope,</hi> the wiſe in heart may ſee that thou, and others are the deceived and deluded, whilſt thou would caſt it upon <hi>Thomas White;</hi> and the Reader may ſee who is the lyar, and his burden he muſt bear.</p>
            <p>Towards the beginning of the fifth page of thy Book thou ſayeſt, <hi>you practice waſhing, becauſe the Lord hath appointed you ſo to do, and are not like many in our day, or like</hi> Naaman <hi>the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyrian, that thinks it a buſineſs too low for them, though it was not too low for Chriſt and his Diſciples, but it was too low for the Phariſees then, who rejected the Counſel of God againſt themſelves, and were not baptized of him,</hi> Luke 7.30.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>James Pope</hi> thou mighteſt have done well to have produced thy commiſſion, that ſo thy practice with it might have been compared, that ſo whether thou exceeds or falls ſhort, might have been underſtood by the Reader, until that be done, thy ſaying the Lord hath appointed you ſo to do, is no more then he that takes away my goods wrongfully, &amp; without my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and yet ſaith, he doth it by Authority, but can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce none, ſaving his luſt and ſtrong deſire after my property
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:172575:10"/>to make himſelf rich, having nothing of his own to live up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>And for ſome being like</hi> Naaman <hi>the Aſſyrian,</hi> &amp;c. If thou kneweſt that there was a Prophet in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> thou wouldſt know who they are that are like <hi>Naaman</hi> the Aſſyrian, that call the light of Chriſt (with which every one that comes into the world is lighted, and checks and reproves for ſin) natural, and the checks of a natural conſcience, and is not ſufficient to lead to ſalvation, as was affirmed at the diſpute at <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable,</hi> by the Baptiſts ſome time ſince, and of later times have been often ſo ſaid by thoſe called Baptiſts; are not theſe moſt like <hi>Naaman,</hi> that deſpiſe the true Prophets waſhing, and is it not yet more evident that theſe are the deſpiſed, and therefore the leproſie remains, though they ſay they ſee; and are not theſe wrath like <hi>Naaman,</hi> and go their way from the light, like him, expecting ſome ſudden irreſiſtible power to fall from heaven upon them, and to make them willing; but will not come to the light in them to wait in it for power to overcome, and do not they wait for ſuch a thing, but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not believe that the Kingdom of Heaven is in the Phariſees, nor that the light which reproves the drunkard and lyar for their evil, is a ſpiritual light, and ſufficient to lead them to ſalvation; but ſay as <hi>Naaman</hi> did, <hi>behold I thought he would have come out to me and ſtand and call on the Name of the Lord his God, and ſtrike his hand over the place, and recover the leper,</hi> &amp;c. Are not you Baptiſts like <hi>Naaman</hi> in this alſo in your own thoughts, limiting the holy one of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſetting bounds to his worſhip? as if God could not be worſhipped a right, if men and women did not go down into the water; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord is appearing in a way to diſappoint the wiſdom of the wiſe, and to fruſtrate the thoughts of the prudent, who think as <hi>Naaman</hi> did, that they know how God will bring to paſſe the great things promiſed, and accompliſh the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings upon his people looked for; but they are miſtaken as <hi>Naaman</hi> was, and ſtumbling at the contemptibleneſs of the true Prophets counſel, as he did, and the Phariſees did, when they reject the light and would not believe in it, that they might be the children of it, and ſuch were thoſe thou ſpeaks of, in <hi>Luke</hi> 7.30. who fruſtrated the Counſel of God within themſelves (as it is in the Margent of the Bible) not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:172575:10"/>being baptized of him, thoſe in the verſe before being baptized with the Baptiſm of <hi>John,</hi> and ſo he that hath an ear may hear, and an eye may ſee who they are that are like <hi>Naaman</hi> the Aſſyrian, and like the Phariſees who fruſt rate the counſel of God within themſelves not being baptized of him; but wilt not thou be inraged like <hi>Naaman,</hi> if my counſel pleaſe not thee, as the Prophets did not like <hi>Naaman,</hi> if I ſhould ſay that whilſt thou compares others to be like <hi>Naaman,</hi> art thy ſelf with many of thy brethren (that differ in their underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings from thee about Election and reprobation, and yet you walk ſweetly together in your fellowſhip, as thou ſayeſt) like him ſpoken of in <hi>Job</hi> 8.15. viz. <hi>He ſhall lean upon his houſe but it ſhall not ſtand, he ſhall hold it faſt but it ſhall not endure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the fifth page, thou returns an anſwer to <hi>Th. Whites</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, <hi>viz.</hi> try your ſelves by the witneſs of God in your conſciences, whether you are come to the Church in God, which is the ground and pillar of Truth; and ſaith that as the Churches in <hi>Judea</hi> were in Chriſt, who was and is God, ſo are we bound to judge of the Churches in <hi>England;</hi> but thou not daring to leave it ſo, brings in a parentheſis, which was well thought of to ſave thy head, <hi>viz.</hi> (walking in the ſame order and profeſſing the ſame faith) and then comes in to be in Chriſt, for before the parentheſis they were not in Chriſt, and it is as plain by adding of the parentheſis they are out of Chriſt; ſo that without it, thou durſt not ſtand to vindicate them, and by thy adding of it, thou haſt at once un-churched them all, and ſo are Chriſts words made good, he that will ſave his life ſhall loſe it, for where are thoſe Churches, among the people called Baptiſts (of whom I ſpeak) that walk in the order of thoſe <hi>Paul</hi> writ unto in his <hi>Epiſtle;</hi> nay are not your Churches ſo far from being like thoſe, that if <hi>Paul</hi> were alive, he would rather expreſſe himſelf by weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over you for your diſorder (as he did over ſome amongſt the <hi>Philippians,</hi> whoſe ſteps you rather follow) then thoſe that he rejoyced to behold their order? <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.18. of whom he had often told them and now ſaith he) tell you even weeping, that they are the enemies to the Croſs of Chriſt, and their end is deſtruction, who minde earthly things, and are not thoſe thou calls Churches in <hi>England</hi> minding earthly things, and ſome making too much proviſions for their bellies, &amp; others
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:172575:11"/>glorying in their ſhame, as flattering Titles and fooliſh apparrel and ſuch like? and wouldſt thou have us to judge every ſuch member to be of the Church in God? nay in him is light, and no darkneſs at all, and he who judges ſuch Churches, and ſuch members to be rather Synagogues of Satan, then Churches of Saints, judges righteous judgement, though <hi>James Pope</hi> call it by another name; for he is ſubject to miſtake as his Book plentifully makes it manifeſt, eſpecially hear where he would have thoſe members called living ſtones, or a Church in God, who differ in their underſtandings about Election and reprobation, and what and how many Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances Chriſt hath appointed to be uſed in his Church, which firſt <hi>James Pope</hi> and his brethren are to agree in, and conclude upon, before thoſe who are led by the ſame ſpirit that <hi>Paul</hi> was can rejoyce in your order; but rather mourns in ſecret for your diſorder, and cryes to the Lord to open the eyes of your underſtandings, and to give you the Spirit of wiſdom and Revelation for the acknowledgement of him, that ye may know what is the hope of his calling, and what the riches of the glory of his inheritance in the Saints, and what is the exceeding greatneſs of his power to us-ward who believe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the working of the might of his power, which he wrought in Chriſt, when he raiſed him from the dead, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ſayeſt, that Baptiſm by fire was promiſed and performed in the ſecond of the Acts and ſome other places; but experimentally nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the</hi> Quakers, <hi>nor any other that thou knoweſt of, doth know it,</hi> if they do, let them make it manifeſt by their ſpeaking in <hi>ſtrange tongues, miracles,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for ſo all could do that the Lord Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized with the Holy Ghoſt and fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas,</hi> Doth not the Saints know things now exper men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally, as well as they did in former times? herein thou haſt ſhewed thy nakedneſs, and of what kind thy knowledge is now (which from me thou wouldſt not have born) if I ſhould have called thy knowledge natural or traditional, as it muſt needs be, if it be not experimental, and ſo is knowledge falſely ſo called, for I deſire to know nothing but what I know experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally in the worſhip and ſervice of God; for all other knowledge doth but puff up; and to it I deſire to be a fool
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:172575:11"/>that I may know things not by thinking, but certainly; and the tongues by which thoſe ſpeak now who are Baptized with the Holy Ghoſt and fire, are as ſtrange to this generation as thoſe were ſtrange to that generation then; and maiſt thou not as well ſay, there is none that thou knows of that are now Baptized with the holy Ghoſt, as to ſay there is none that thou knows Baptized with fire, &amp; maiſt thou not as truly ſay, that there is none that thou knows of now Baptized with the Holy Ghoſt, becauſe none now ſpeaks with thoſe ſtrange tongues, nor doth thoſe Miracles thou ſpeaks of; for they went toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then, and they are not parted now, except by thoſe who knows neither experimentally; and if thou knew any Baptiſm aright, or him that is mightier then <hi>John,</hi> thou mighteſt know Baptizing with the Holy Ghoſt and fire; or if thou know him whoſe fan is in his hand; but art thou not in truth as ignorant of his fan as of his fire, and becauſe of thy ignorance of both, the chaff remains unburnt up, and the chaff ungathered into the garner; and therefore I tell thee plainly <hi>(James Pope)</hi> thou and thy brethren muſt yet know a terrible day of threſhing before the Word of the Lord you know that is as a hammer and fire, until then your words are but as chaff to the wheat, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.28, 29 and <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.10, 11, 12. Be not angry if in love to thee I ask thee a Queſtion; <hi>viz.</hi> Are not many of the Baptiſts now that are Baptized with water, as ignorant of the Holy Ghoſts Baptiſm as thoſe Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of <hi>John</hi> in <hi>John</hi> 1 35, 36, 37. who followed Chriſt and left <hi>John</hi> were? who at the 41. <hi>verſ.</hi> ſaith, We have found the Meſſias, which they had not while they were with <hi>John;</hi> but in this you Baptiſts are ſhort of <hi>John,</hi> for he was not angry when his Diſciples left him and went to Chriſt: ſee that you imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate him in this alſo as well as his outward waſhing.</p>
            <p>And for thy anſwer to what is the flaming ſword, thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſts thy ignorance of it (as of the Baptiſm with fire) in ſaying, <hi>If thou meaneſt the work of grace,</hi> &amp;c. He meant as he ſpake, and if indeed thou kneweſt it, thou would have retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned another anſwer, and not when a queſtion is asked about a particular, then to anſwer if thou mean <hi>the work of grace in you;</hi> and here thou makeſt good thy former words, <hi>viz.</hi> That thy knowledge is not experimental no more of the flaming
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:172575:12"/>ſword, then of Baptiſm by fire; and if thou art miſtaken in this, then doth not thy ignorance appear of what follows by thy own confeſſion, and it is no uncharitableneſs ſo to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, <hi>viz.</hi> That you have not felt the quickning power of the Lord raiſing up a Seed, and bringing forth a birth in you which is not of the world; but contrary to the world, which is leading out of the vanities thereof, and cauſes them to bear the croſs.</p>
            <p>Then thou ſaiſt, <hi>The Baptiſts are for ſigns and wonders, and gazing ſtocks in the earth;</hi> and thou ſaiſt, <hi>Some of us have been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached for the Name of Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c <hi>though we have at this day much reſt from the rage of our enemies.</hi> What confuſion is here, firſt to ſay the Baptiſts <hi>are for ſigns and wonders,</hi> &amp;c. and then to ſay (with the ſame breath as it were) ſome of us have been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached, &amp;c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and though we have at this day reſt, &amp;c. How can theſe things hang together? Is not the reſt that you now have in the fleſh, and in that ſame nature that the world is in? And is not the ſeed ſpoken of before, unraiſed up, but rather in <hi>Babylon</hi> then in <hi>Canaan?</hi> And was it not better with you then when you were as gazing ſtocks to the world, then now when you are become their companions in their folly, &amp; vanity, and <hi>cuſtoms</hi> and <hi>faſhions</hi> which thou ſpeaks of in thy next lines, &amp;c? And thy ingenious confeſſion <hi>of the reforming work that is yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind</hi> (I own) but remember it is he that confeſſeth and forſaketh that finds mercy, and take heed of covering your evil cuſtoms with good names, as thou in thy following words pleads for, leaſt thou ſpoil thy former confeſſion and cavil againſt what thou ſeemedſt even now to wind up into a penitent confeſſion; and ſo thou thy ſelf and thy brethren be the very men that thou ſpeakeſt of in the former page, that are like <hi>Naaman the Aſſyrian,</hi> that not onely thinks the cuſtoms and faſhions of the world (which the people called <hi>Quakers</hi> ſtand witneſſes againſt on truths behalf) too low for you to ſtoop unto, but alſo in that you are like <hi>Naaman the Aſſyrian</hi> in this particular, who after he was waſhed confeſſed to the true God, in the 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 5.15, 17. and 18. <hi>ver.</hi> and ſaid he would not ſacrifice to other Gods but to the Lord, and yet (like thee) in the next words begins to plead thy caſe, or rather really to diſpence with the light of Chriſt in his Conſcience, ſaying, <hi>In this thing the Lord
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:172575:12"/>pardon thy ſervant, that when my Maſter goeth into the houſe of Rim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to worſhip there, and he leaneth on my hand, and I bow my ſelf in the houſe of Rimmon: when I bow down my ſelf in the houſe of Rimmon, the Lord pardon thy ſervant in this thing.</hi> Read your ſelves you that are called Baptiſts, and behold your faces as in a glaſs; how many of ſuch ſpots, <hi>Naaman</hi>-like, have you in your faces? is there no houſe of <hi>Rimmon</hi> now, that you need to beg pardon for bowing in it, if not for repairing of it, and not onely ſo, but for maitaining thoſe Prieſts that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in this <hi>Rimmons</hi> houſe? And here ſurely you had need of pardon, and in this you exceed <hi>Naaman,</hi> for he onely bowed in <hi>Rimmons</hi> houſe, but you pay Tithes or maintenance to <hi>Rimmons</hi> Prieſts, or ſome not much unlike to them, and ſome of you do hear them, and call them good men; and therefore leave off any more naming of <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Aſſyrian,</hi> except to manifeſt your own tranſgreſſions; for had you Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts in <hi>England</hi> been faithful to God, according to your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions and judgements, had Tithes been this day ſtanding in <hi>England,</hi> and had there been a hireling Miniſtry in <hi>England,</hi> as it is at this day? had you Baptiſts and ſeparated people been faithful to God; but then would you have been ſtill gazing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocks to many, as ſome of you have bin in years paſt, while you kept your firſt love, and abode in your tenderneſs and integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. But ah! dear people conſider your loſs, what an exchange have you made, that looſe your acquaintance with God to gain peace with the world; and is it not plain, in that many of you (through the ſubtile diſtinctions found out by ſome of your Teachers) can now do thoſe things without remorſe which ſometimes you durſt not do? And how do you like <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> diſpence with ſome of Chriſts Commands, &amp; cry up others for commands, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> he hath not commanded? Is not tithe, mint and cummin paid, while the great and weightier matters are left undone? (do not ſay I charge you falſely) is not reſpect of perſons forbidden? And is not all ſwearing forbidden? Do you not in theſe and other things, not onely reſpect perſons, and make God ſo to be, but reſpect his Commands alſo, pleading for ſome and neglectieg others? Is not this like <hi>Naaman,</hi> after many good words and fair con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions? Do you not know that faithfulneſs in theſe things
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:172575:13"/>would ſtill keep you at the ſame diſtance from the world, not onely to have been, but ſo to continue as ſigns and wonders? but was it not better than with you then it is now? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore return to your firſt love, and cry in truth and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) mightily to the Lord (not like <hi>Naaman</hi>) to pardon you not onely in theſe things, but for all your unfaithfulneſs to God, that in the light that lets you ſee your evils, you may wait to be waſhed from them by the blood of Jeſus Chriſt; and then you need not plead for any heatheniſh cuſtoms to manifeſt your duty by, but in faithfulneſs to God yield obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Parents, Maſters, Magiſtrates, &amp;c. which is ſufficiently manifeſt by yielding obedience to all Juſt Commands, and is honour enough to all theſe (and other) relations, that they have the honour that comes from God onely given to them, with which they ought to be contented, and not to ſeek ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour one of another, nor to be angry becauſe their perſons are not reſpected, nor flattering titles given to them.</p>
            <p>Then thou comes to anſwer <hi>Thomas Whites</hi> Queries. 1. <q rend="margQuotes">What Command or Commiſſion have ye or any men to Baptize with water from Chriſt declared in any Scripture, which Command did not as well extend to <hi>Paul</hi> who was an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, as to any of you?</q>
            </p>
            <p>To this thou ſaiſt, <hi>Paul had the ſame Command or Commiſſion to Baptize with water as any man now hath, or any man ever had; for the Command to Baptize in water was given to Chriſts Diſciples, and was not tied to the Office of the Apoſtleſhip, but as more Diſciples were made ſucceſſively, ſo were they ſucceſſively to be taught to obſerve what ever Chriſt had commanded them,</hi> viz. <hi>the preceding Diſciples; and ſo though</hi> Paul <hi>as an Apoſtle was not ſent to Baptize, yet as a Diſciple he had good warrant ſo to do; yet ſeeing ſome in the Church of</hi> Corinth <hi>were ready to Idolize his Miniſtry, and the work of Baptiſm might as well be done by other Diſciples that were not Apoſtles, he thanks God he Baptized no more of them, to prevent, no doubt, any ſaying he had Baptized them into his own Name.</hi> This is thy anſwer, and thou ſums up thy anſwer in theſe words; <hi>Thus you ſee</hi> Pauls <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to Baptize with water, as good as any mans now, and ſo his Commiſſion and ours alſo are both good, which is a full anſwer to the Query.</hi> But ſuch a one as darkens Councel by words without knowledge; for it is not doubted but <hi>Pauls</hi> Commiſſion was as
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:172575:13"/>good as yours; but it is queſtioned whether yours be ſo good as his, ſeeing <hi>Pauls</hi> Command being good to him, makes not yours good to you, no more then his Faith being right makes yours right. But in this thy anſwer, thou grants that you have no Command to Baptize with water, &amp;c. But the ſame belonged to <hi>Paul</hi> as well as you: and to ſave the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence which muſt needs follow, <hi>viz.</hi> that you do that which you are not ſent to do, ſaying, you have no Command but what <hi>Paul</hi> had: and he ſaith, he was not ſent to Baptize, and no more are any of you by thy own confeſſion, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is high time to leave it off. But thou not being willing to part with it ſo, like <hi>Micah,</hi> art ready to ſay, <hi>What have I more, and what is this you ſay unto me, what aileth thee?</hi> Judg. 18.23, 24. And therefore ſaiſt thou, that the Command was given to Chriſts Diſciples, and was not tyed to the Office of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtleſhip; What a ſlubberly anſwer is this? Was not thoſe to whom the Command was given Apoſtles? are they not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Apoſtles in <hi>Mat.</hi> 10? <hi>And when he had called unto him his twelve Diſciples, he gave them power,</hi> &amp;c. and at the next verſ. <hi>Now the names of the twelve Apoſtles are theſe,</hi> &amp;c. and at Luke 6.13. <hi>And when it was day, he called unto him his Diſciples, and of them he choſe twelve, whom alſo he named Apoſtles;</hi> So that theſe were alſo Apoſtles as well as Diſciples to whom the Command was given: Diſciples when he called them, and out of them choſe twelve; and when he had taught them what to do, then they are called Apoſtles: Diſciples when they came to Chriſt, Apoſtles when they went from Chriſt, and were impowered what to do: and Chriſt calling them Diſciples in <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. doth no more take away the Apoſtleſhip, then Chriſt calling them Apoſtles in <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. and <hi>Luke</hi> 6. takes away their Diſcipleſhip: and therefore to ſay <hi>Paul</hi> was not ſent to Baptize as an Apoſtle, is to ſay, <hi>Paul</hi> was not ſent to preach as an Apoſtle, except <hi>Paul</hi> had one Commiſſion to preach, and another to Baptize, ſeeing that Commiſſion hinted at in <hi>Matthew</hi> requires both: beſides, is not this to devide <hi>Paul,</hi> or rather Chriſt in <hi>Paul,</hi> that he did ſome things miniſterially as an Apoſtle, and other things as a Diſciple, as if he were ſometimes an Apoſtle and no Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciple, and ſometimes a Diſciple and no Apoſtle: or that <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould diſſemble with the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> to write to them as an
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:172575:14"/>Apoſtle, and to thank God that he had Baptized no more but thoſe few he names, and gives this reaſon for it, becauſe he was not ſent to Baptize, but to preach the Goſpel: when as by thy own confeſſion he was ſent as he was a Diſciple to Baptize as well as others, and knew it (as well as <hi>James Pope</hi>) if it had been ſo; and had not <hi>Paul</hi> by removing one block out of the way, <hi>viz.</hi> (preventing a jealouſie, leaſt he ſhould be thought to Baptize in his own name) laid a greater ſtumbling block in the way, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſlight the Ordinance of Baptiſm, and all thoſe that ſhould Baptize with water, though as Diſciples, <hi>Paul</hi> not explaining his meaning (to be) as <hi>James Pope</hi> ſaith it was, <hi>viz.</hi> that he meant as an Apoſtle he was not ſent, but as a Diſciple he might &amp; did: and might not <hi>Paul</hi> as well have left off preaching to prevent the jealouſie of preaching in his own name as well as Baptizing, ſeeing one was commanded in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion as well as the other, &amp; was or might have been idolized as well as Baptizing: but in truth, <hi>Paul</hi> had no more Command to Baptize with water then to Circumciſe, yet he did both up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occaſion to remove ſtumbling blocks, and to ſtrengthen the weak, and all for the furtherance of the Goſpel. And Chriſts calling them Diſciples in one place, after he had once choſen them, hinders them not from being Apoſtles, no more then his calling them Apoſtles in another place, hinders them from being Diſciples; for ſometimes he called them by the name of Diſciples, and ſometimes by the name of Apoſtles, as <hi>Luke</hi> 22.14. <hi>And when the hour was come, he ſate down and the twelve Apoſtles with him:</hi> and this was before he ſent them forth in <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. but is not this a new invention, ſaying that <hi>Paul</hi> as a Diſciple was ſent, but not as an Apoſtle: ſeeing the old cover is found out to be too narrow, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>Paul</hi> was not ſent ſo much to Baptize as to preach: and therefore where it is ſaid, not ſent, is meant (ſay ſome) not ſo much; as labour not for the bread that periſheth, &amp;c. that is (ſay ſome) not ſo much for bread that periſhes: but you not being able to prove that <hi>Paul</hi> was ſent at all to baptize with water; but it may be eaſily proved, that to labour at all is not onely lawful but commanded: but that <hi>Paul</hi> was ſent at all to Baptize with water, yet remains to be proved: and to ſay that he did Baptize with water, and therefore was ſent, proves no more
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:172575:14"/>that he was ſent to Baptize with water, then becauſe he did Circumciſe, proves he was ſent to Circumciſe: but in thy ſaying it belonged not to <hi>Pauls</hi> Office, and therefore he might leave it; in this thou haſt truly concluded, that a man may be ſent of God, as <hi>Paul</hi> was, and yet not Baptize with water, as not belonging to his Office, and for this ingenious confeſſion of thine, I may as truly confeſs to thee alſo, that there are many that do Baptize with water, who are not ſent by God ſo to do; and of this thy Brethren may take notice, how thou thy ſelf haſt anſwered the Objection which is ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten made by them, and ſeems to lie ſo much in their way, <hi>viz.</hi> if we that are called <hi>Quakers</hi> were led by the ſame ſpirit that the Primitive Saints were led by, ſurely then we would do the ſame things that they did, as to practiſe water Baptiſm, &amp;c. Which Objection thou haſt anſwered to the ſatisfaction of the Objectors; in that thou haſt found out a man ſent of God, and led by his Spirit, and yet might lawfully let water Baptiſm alone to others, as not belonging to his Office.</p>
            <p>
               <q>2. The next Query propounded, is, whether the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward waſhing with water (which is but the ſhadow) and <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſm, or the inward waſhing or cleanſing by the Spirit, which is the Baptiſm of Chriſt; Which of theſe (I ſay) is that one Baptiſm that <hi>Paul</hi> wrote of? Or why writes he but of one there, if both might be continued?</q>
            </p>
            <p>To this Query thou anſwereſt like one altogether ignorant of the Spirits Baptiſm, like thoſe Baptiſts in <hi>Acts</hi> 19.2. onely with this difference, thou haſt read there is a Holy Ghoſt and a Baptiſm ſo called, of which they had not heard, but thou haſt read, and like them haſt been (it may be) Baptized with <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſm, who indeed Baptized with water; but he of whom <hi>John</hi> bore witneſs, Baptized with a better Baptiſm, who was to increaſe, but <hi>John</hi> and his water Baptiſm was to decreaſe, for <hi>John</hi> was ſent to prepare his way.</p>
            <p>In thy anſwer to the Query, thou ſaiſt, <hi>There are three Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions; Firſt, that it is but a ſhadow. Secondly, that it is</hi> Johns <hi>Baptiſm. Thirdly, that the waſhing and cleanſing by the Spirit is Chriſts Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the firſt <hi>thou ſaiſt thou ſhalt let it paſs; to the ſecond thou pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds a queſtion,</hi> and then follows with a ſecond queſtion,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:172575:15"/>
               <hi>whether</hi> John <hi>were a Miniſter of the Law or Goſpel;</hi> and then thou further Queries, <hi>Whether there were any other difference between</hi> Johns <hi>and Chriſts, then that one taught and prepared for Chriſt to come, and the other taught to believe in him that was already come,</hi> &amp;c. What ſhuffling is here to avoid a plain queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi> in ſhort which is no more then for thee to anſwer, what that one Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm is which <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, whether it be water or the Spirits Baptiſm? And if both were to continue, why writes he but of one? And to anſwer this plain Queſtion, thou asks Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions and propounds further Queries, as if the way to reſolve one Queſtion, were to propound two others; or as if to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer one Query, were further to Query: but it is commonly the anſwer of him or them that have no further nor bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter anſwer to return. But thou further anſwers in the third place and ſaiſt, <hi>Whereas it is implied that the inward waſhing and cleanſing by the Spirit is Chriſts Baptiſm, I do not know that any Scripture calls it Chriſts Baptiſm, or Baptiſm at all,</hi> &amp;c. Thou mighteſt have left out this thirdly, except it had been on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to manifeſt thy ignorance of the Scripture and Spirits Baptiſm: thou needs not have ſaid, <hi>I do not know that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward waſhing and cleanſing by the Spirit is Chriſts Baptiſm;</hi> For what difference is there between inward waſhing by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and inward Baptizing by the Spirit, is it not all one, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one is tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and the other is left in <hi>Greek</hi> untranflated? And ſo whilſt thou ſaiſt, thou doſt not know that any Scripture calls it Chriſts waſhing or baptiſm, confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and calls it inward waſhing thy ſelf, ſo that by thy own confeſſion there is no more difference between the inward waſhing and cleanſing by the Spirit, and Chriſts bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, then there is between baptizing in <hi>Greek,</hi> and waſhing in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> which is all one; and the word bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm might as well have been tranſlated waſhing in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Scripture, as in one place, had it not made for the upholding of the Trade of the Tranſlators, and for the continuing of much idolatry and ignorance in the world; and whereas thou ſayeſt it is not called Chriſts Baptiſm, what Baptiſm was that the Apoſtles ſpeak of, 1 Cor. 12.13. <hi>For by one ſpirit are we all baptized into one body, whether we be</hi> Jews <hi>or</hi> Gentiles; and what Baptiſm was that which <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3, 4. <q rend="margQuotes">by which they were baptized into Chriſt and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:172575:15"/>his death, and were buried with Chriſt by Baptiſm, and by it planted into the likeneſs of his death, whereby they knew that the old man was crucified with him, that the body of ſin might be deſtroyed, that henceforth they might not ſerve ſin; for he that was thus dead and buried with Chriſt,</q> was free from ſin; which your water doth not do; nay do not you who are waſhed with water plead againſt free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from ſin, and ſay it is not attainable in this world? and therefore it is ſtrongly to be ſuſpected that as your Baptiſm is wrong ſo is your faith alſo, ſeeing the Scripture ſaith as many as have been baptized into Chriſt, have put on Chriſt, and put off the old man with his deeds, by being planted into the likeneſs of his death, and by being buried with him by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and in the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. where the Apoſtle ſaith they were waſhed, and ſanctified, and juſtified by the ſpirit, &amp;c. what difference is there by being waſhed or cleanſed by the ſpirit, and by being baptized by the ſpirit, ſeeing waſhing and Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing is all one, and if thou wert come to the full aſſurance of faith, and kneweſt what it was to have thy heart ſprinkled from an evil conſcience, then thou wouldſt know what that pure water was with wch the Saints had their bodies waſhed, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22. But thou concludeſt that Chriſts Baptiſm is not now in being, becauſe thoſe tongues and miracles thou ſpeaks of are not in being that thou know of, and ſo juſtifies thy ſelf that the one baptiſm is meant water baptiſm, &amp; Chriſts baptiſm or the Baptiſm of the ſpirit was ſome extraordinary thing, <hi>and was to confer upon them a larger meaſure of gifts, fitting then to ſpread the Goſpel,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and therefore one principal gift beſtowed by that Baptiſm was the gift of tongues,</hi> (to this I ſpake before about fire Baptiſm) as in <hi>Acts</hi> the ſecond, and ſaith other places both before in the ſixth page and now, but names none; by which I conclude thou haſt no place to prove the Holy Ghoſts Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm thou ſpeaks of, but that of <hi>Acts</hi> 2. and what ground thou haſt to call that (fire) Chriſts Baptiſm, or the Baptiſm pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed that Chriſt ſhould come withal, I know not, ſince there is not one word in that ſecond of the <hi>Acts</hi> at the beginning (that ſpeaks of Baptiſm) where it is ſaid, <hi>there came a ſound from Heaven, as of a ruſhing mighty wind, and it filled all the houſe where they were ſitting, And there appeared unto them cloven tongues, like as of fire, and it ſate upon each of them; and they
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:172575:16"/>were all filled with the Ghoſt, and began to ſpeak with other tongues as the ſpirit gave them utterance.</hi> Where is this called the Baptiſm of Chriſt, or the Baptiſm of the Holy Ghoſt? the word Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm is no more named here neither in Greek nor Engliſh; and yet this thou wouldſt have by all means to be the only Baptiſm of the Holy Ghoſt promiſed, and ſome other places, where both the word Baptiſm in Greek and the word waſhing in Engliſh is ſpoken off, muſt not be the Baptiſm of the ſpirit, that was promiſed and was to continue, when outward water was to ceaſe; but why ſhould thou ſpeak of miracles and tongues ſo much, ſeeing tongues were for a ſign, not for them which believed but for them which believed not, and thou accounts thy ſelf a believer, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.22.</p>
            <p>But <hi>James Pope,</hi> why doſt thou ſeem to grant inward waſhing and cleanſing by the ſpirit to be a waſhing or Baptiſm of the ſpirit, ſeeing thou haſt ſpent ſo much time to prove inward waſhing and cleanſing to be none of the ſpirits baptiſm, and yet ſums up the query thy ſelf in theſe words, <hi>whether the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm of water, or the inward waſhing and cleanſing by the ſpirit, be the one Baptiſm which</hi> Paul <hi>writs of, or why writs he but of one, if both muſt be continued; to which thou grants both muſt be continued, and yet ſaith it is water Baptiſm he writs of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that thou ſeems to grant what thou wouldſt deny, and to deny what thou wouldſt grant; but thou art in a ſtrait, and truth is too hard for thee; for if thou grant the ſpirits Baptiſm to continue, then thy water Baptiſm muſt down, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is but one, and therefore of the two thou hadſt rather the ſpirits Baptiſm ſhould ceaſe then thine, and yet if thou ſhould deny inward baptizing or cleanſing to be out of uſe, then thou wert no Chriſtian; and therefore thou haſt ſowed as good a covering together as fig leaves will make to hide thy nakedneſs withal, and to ſave thy water Baptiſm, and thinks to do it by calling inward baptizing with the Holy Ghoſt, inward cleanſing and waſhing by the ſpirit; and ſo ſets up two words to contend each with other, whilſt thou there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thinkeſt to amaze the Reader, that thou may eſcape with thy water to be the one Baptiſm that is to continue, and yet in thy firſt anſwer ſaith, both muſt continue, inward Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm <hi>becauſe no entrance into the Kingdom without it, and water
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:172575:16"/>muſt continue, becauſe it is Chriſts Ordinance fitted to the</hi> New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as Circumciſion was to the Old; In thy next Book <hi>(James)</hi> prove it an Ordinance commanded by Chriſt to be practiced after his Aſcention, in plain words, and not by an invented conſequence, leaſt you are found guilty of that for which you condemned the Prieſts of <hi>England, viz.</hi> for proving their Baptiſm by a conſequence; and will not this be much to your ſhame, to have your Commiſion to prove by a conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, and not by plain and poſitive Scripture, for a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner by conſequence onely is no Commiſſioner. But <hi>(James)</hi> me thinks thou comes too near the Prieſts of <hi>England</hi> in bringing Circumciſion and Baptiſm together, doſt thou not lay thy ſelf open to ſome diſadvantage in this? was one Ordinance a type of another, or one figure a type of another figure? what confuſion is here? is not this Prieſts baptiſm? was not the Circumciſion of the fleſh a type of the Circumciſion of the heart? and was not water Baptiſm a figure of the inward waſhing by the Lavor of regeneration, and is called a figure, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. of that that ſaves, not the waſhing away the filth of the fleſh, which was the outward baptiſm, but the inward waſhing, and anſwer of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience by the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt, which is known by all who have their hearts ſprinkled from an evil conſcience by the fleſh of Jeſus Chriſt. How is Baptiſm fitted any more to the new witneſs then any other thing commanded or practiced by the Saints? if thou knew the new witneſs which he that believes hath in himſelf, thou wouldſt know there is no more outward water in it then outward fire; but thou ſpeaks words by tradition and underſtandeſt not what thou ſayeſt, was Circumciſion any otherwiſe fitted to the old witneſs or Teſtament then as a figure of the true cutting off from the body of ſin by the Circumciſion of Chriſt? and is Baptiſm any otherwiſe fitted to the new Teſtament then as a figure alſo? and when the ſubſtance is come, they both end in him who is the ſubſtance. And for thy ſaying, <hi>Chriſts Diſciples were to teach ſucceeding Diſciples what ever he had commanded them,</hi> &amp;c. but water is not mentioned to be commanded them by Chriſt, and therefore not to teach water, having it not in charge. Again thou ſayeſt, <hi>he promiſed his preſence with them to the end of the world,</hi> if his preſence with them, then is he not a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:172575:17"/>to them, and are they not to receive the word at is mouth? <hi>ſeeing God ſpeaks by him in theſe laſt dayes,</hi> and he is the ſame yeſterday to day and for ever; or was and did Chriſt only ſpeak with and to his twelve diſciples, and they to deliver over by tradition what he told them? or were the Saints without Chriſts preſence for divers hundred years after his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of the world, before the New Teſtament was ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together, and bound in one Book, ſeeing the Epiſtles were ſcattered up and down in divers parts of the world ſome many hundred miles diſtant one Epiſtle from another? and how long after, and by whoſe command were they gathered together? or is Chriſts preſence with his people, and yet he ſpeaks not to them imediately? or is Chriſt leſs powerful then he was? or is his love abated? or did he ſpeak once for all? and will he never ſpeak more imediately? or elſe what doth Chriſts preſence ſignifie now if not to ſpeak to them, lead them, and ſave them? otherwiſe what is man the better for ſuch a preſence as he knows not nor is not ſenſible of? or hath Chriſt ceaſed to be a King, ſeeing <hi>where the preſence of a King is there is power?</hi> or is a man only to believe he hath Chriſts preſence with him, <hi>while other Lords have Dominion over him?</hi> or hath Chriſt left his people to pick out his worſhip as well as he can here and there a little, out of all the Epiſtles and other Books by their own judgements and underſtandings? Is not this to make the New Teſtament inferior to the Old; where <hi>Iſraels</hi> Laws were together in Tables, and in ſome particular places and books, as <hi>Deut Levit.</hi> &amp;c? If you be the ſucceeding Diſciples, and are to obſerve all things that thoſe were to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and had in command? why are you not going into all Nations to Preach the Goſpel in every creature, but ſtay at home in your country? or have you not Chriſts preſence with you, and ſo dare not venture too far? but <hi>what ſingular thing do you do,</hi> whereby it may appear you have Chriſts preſence with you, and are indeed the ſucceeding Diſciples thou ſpeaks of? or is it not rather manifeſt, you are none of his Diſciples, ſeeing he never taught nor practiced ſuch cuſtoms and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formities to the world, as are practiced among many called bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts; beſides this legible mark, they do not love one another, but bite and devour one another about thoſe things they call
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:172575:17"/>Chriſts Ordinances and appointments, and if this be true which Chriſt ſaid, <hi>viz. by this ſhall all men know you are my Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, if you love one another;</hi> then whoſe Diſciples are thoſe who hate one another, how is Chriſts preſence with them, while theſe things abide among them?</p>
            <p>Then thou gives thy reaſon why thou ſayeſt, <hi>that of water is the one Baptiſm</hi> Paul <hi>writes</hi> of, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe the other is not called Baptiſm, but it is called <hi>waſhing by the ſpirit,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. &amp; divers other places as before is proved; ſo it is either the thing or the word thou denyes, if the thing, it is ſufficiently proved to be called waſhing which is all one with baptizing, as <hi>Luke</hi> 11.38. <hi>And when the Phariſee ſaw it, he marvelled that he had not firſt baptized before dinner, or waſhed</hi> as ſome Tranſlators read it. If the word baptiſm be that which thou denyes, where is the word Baptiſm attributed to fire, or where is it ſaid they were baptized with fire? and yet thou urges the ſecond of <hi>Acts</hi> to prove Baptiſm with fire, when there is not the word bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm there, onely, like as of fire. But then thou ſayeſt, <hi>if it were called Baptiſm, yet were it a Metaphorical, and not a proper Baptiſm,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>James,</hi> thou mayeſt remember in thy ſix page thou ſayeſt, <hi>to the Law and to the teſtimony, if they ſpeak not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this word, it is becauſe there is no light in them;</hi> out of thy own mouth mayeſt thou be judged, where is there one ſuch a word in the Law or teſtimony, as Metaphorical? if it be not there to be found, may it not be ſaid (without offence) thou ſpeaks not according to the Law and teſtimony, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is no light in thee, for thou ſayeſt plainly it is not a proper baptiſm, ſurely <hi>(James)</hi> thou knoweſt it not, and therefore miſcals it, for if ever thou had witneſſed it, or knew what it were to be baptized into Chriſt, and to put on Chriſt, thou would not ſo ſpeak of it, to call it, <hi>not a proper Baptiſm;</hi> What did <hi>John</hi> who baptized with water, baptize with a proper baptiſm, and Chriſt of whom he bore witneſs, baptize with an improper baptiſm, or a baptiſm not proper? was ever ſuch groſſe abſurdities affirmed, as that the meſſenger and ſervant ſhould baptize with the proper Baptiſm, and the Maſter him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with a Baptiſm not proper? Is the ſervant become above his maſter? or is the Maſters work onely Metaphorical and not proper? what is not the waſhing away of ſins a proper
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:172575:18"/>waſhing? and is not the lavor of regeneration a proper waſhing or baptiſing and is not that with wch thoſe Apoſtles and others who were baptized or waſhed by the ſpirit, a proper waſhing or baptizing? and thoſe that had their bodies waſhed with pure water, was not that a proper waſhing? Is not this to darken counſel again by words without knowledge, and by mens traditions and inventions to make void Chriſts commands? is not the waſhing of the ſpirit, the true and proper waſhing, or is the figure in thy eſteem become proper and ſubſtantial, and the ſubſtance and truth become Metaphorical and not proper? and is the waſhing away the filth of the fleſh preferred before the anſwer of a good conſcience, by the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt? and ſo that by thee is called not proper, which is moſt proper, and that Metaphorically which is true, ſubſtantial and real, for whatſoever is ſpiritually ſo, is more ſo then that which is naturally ſo, and that which is moſt real and true is moſt proper: but herein thou apparently ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſts thy ignorance of the true and proper Baptiſm, like thoſe who had <hi>Johns</hi> waſhing, <hi>but knew not whether there were any Holy Ghoſt or not.</hi> Acts 19. mayeſt thou not as well ſay, that Chriſts blood and Chriſts fleſh, which except a man eat and drink, he hath no life in him, is Metaphorical and not proper? though Chriſt ſaith his blood is drink indeed, and his fleſh is meat indeed, and nouriſhes up to eternal life, and is moſt proper food for the children; but is not this as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper in thy judgement, though Chriſt ſaith it is meat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed (mark indeed) not as thou ſayeſt of his Baptiſm but properly, ſubſtantially and indeed? but is not this as hard a ſaying now to many who ſay they are Diſciples, as it was of old, and becauſe of theſe hard ſayings, have not <hi>many Diſciples gone back, and walked no more with him,</hi> Joh. 6.60. &amp; 66.</p>
            <p>Again thou ſayeſt, <hi>the Baptiſm intended by</hi> Paul, Epheſ. 4.5. <hi>is diſtinguiſhed in the ſame place from faith, by which God purifieth the heart, Acts</hi> 15.9. <hi>and Mark</hi> 19.16. (and there is no ſuch chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter nor verſe) <hi>which is the inward waſhing and cleanſing by the ſpirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here thou grants again what thou ſeems to diſpute againſt; which is ſayeſt thou <hi>the inward waſhing and cleanſing by the ſpirit,</hi> ſo that all that thou contends againſt is the word baptizing, or
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:172575:18"/>Baptiſm, where as thou cals it waſhing by the ſpirit; but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes it to be baptizing by the ſpirit, ſo confeſſes it in Engliſh, but denyes it in Greek, but thou ſayeſt it is diſtinguiſhed from faith which waſhes, and therefore not the ſpirits baptizing, or waſhing, and yet calls it thy ſelf the inward waſhing by the ſpirit; ſo thou art but as one that fights with thy own ſhadow. But is not thy confuſion manifeſt to all whoſe eyes are open? &amp; is not this thy reaſon that thou gives (why that baptiſm is not meant the ſpirits baptiſm) <hi>becauſe diſtinguiſhed from faith which waſhes,</hi> &amp;c. is not this reaſon as ſtrong againſt the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> and againſt the <hi>hope,</hi> and againſt the <hi>one Lord and one God,</hi> as againſt the <hi>Baptiſm?</hi> are not all theſe diſtinguiſhed by name, though all one in nature and kind? or is the <hi>Lord</hi> not <hi>God,</hi> becauſe diſtinguiſhed by name? and is not the <hi>ſpirit, God,</hi> becauſe diſtinguiſhed there by name? and is the <hi>hope</hi> not Chriſt, becauſe diſtinguiſhed? what non-ſence and confuſion is here? is the <hi>one baptiſm, or one waſhing,</hi> that is ſo nearly coupled to the <hi>one ſpirit, one Lord</hi> and <hi>one God,</hi> and <hi>one hope</hi> and one faith, not the true or proper <hi>Baptiſm or waſhing</hi> of the ſpirit, becauſe diſtinguiſhed from ſuch which waſhes and purifies? is not by the ſame reaſon the one <hi>hope</hi> which purifies not the true and ſpiritual <hi>hope,</hi> becauſe it is diſtinguiſhed from <hi>faith</hi> which purifies? and by the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the <hi>one ſpirit</hi> is not the true <hi>ſpirit,</hi> becauſe diſtinguiſhed from <hi>faith and hope</hi> which purifies and waſhes, as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6 11. waſhed by the <hi>ſpirit;</hi> but in this Argument alſo (as well as others) is not thy folly made manifeſt to all men (that reads with underſtanding) are all theſe things different in nature becauſe diſtinguiſhed by name? what ignorance is this? doth not thy own Argument make againſt thy ſelf, and thy water Baptiſm, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe <hi>faith,</hi> and <hi>hope,</hi> and the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> and Lord, and God, and Baptiſm are onely diſtinguiſhed by name, and not divided in nature or kind, therefore it muſt needs be intended the <hi>Baptiſm of the ſpirit?</hi> all theſe names being ſpiritual, and onely diſtinguiſhed, but not divided in nature and kind, is to ſpeak of a ſpiritual and inward <hi>hope,</hi> and a ſpiritual and inward <hi>faith,</hi> and a ſpiritual and inward <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>God</hi> above all and through all and in you all; and then ſhould thruſt in, in the midſt of this inward and ſpiritual unity, an outward viſible water, which onely waſhes away
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:172575:19"/>the filth of the fleſh outwardly, is not this to ſet up and to prefer your water, and couple it with and make it equal to the <hi>one Lord,</hi> the <hi>one faith,</hi> the <hi>one God</hi> and <hi>one ſpirit?</hi> and to make the want of outward water and waſhing to be a breach of the union with the <hi>one Lord, and one God, and one faith,</hi> and ſo he that is not outwardly waſhed with outward water is out of the unity with the <hi>one ſpirit, one Lord, and the one God;</hi> for if any of theſe particulars be wanting, the union is not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat but broken, and therefore he that hath not the true <hi>hope</hi> in him, is not in the unity of the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> and he that hath not the true and one <hi>faith,</hi> hath not unity with <hi>God nor Chriſt,</hi> and ſo he that hath not the one <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> hath not the <hi>one Lord,</hi> nor the <hi>one God;</hi> for none of theſe may be ſpared with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the breach of the union in the whole, for he that hath one of theſe, hath all theſe, for they are in unity together, and unites all as with a bond of Peace, where they are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed. So that, thou <hi>James Pope</hi> haſt at once (by thy ſaying this one <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is outward water and waſhing) condemned all the children of the Lord that are not ſo baptized with out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward water, as being out of the unity of <hi>the ſpirit,</hi> and out of the unity with the <hi>one Lord and one God,</hi> and ſo no ſalvation for them; is not this to ſet up another Saviour, or to bring in an outward corruptible creature, and ſet it upon the throne by the Creator? and ſo make outward waſhing with water to be the key to let into the Kingdom of God, and unity of the ſpirit, and without it no union with <hi>God or Chriſt or the ſpirit,</hi> and ſo no ſalvation; therefore ſaid I not truely, thou waſt not willing to part with thy water ſo; but like <hi>Micah, Judges the</hi> 18.24. might well cry out, <hi>you have taken away my gods, and what have I more? and why do you ask me what aileth me?</hi> ſo now it is no wonder you cry out ſo much for your water, ſeeing you joyn it ſo cloſe to the one faith, one Lord, and the one God, that if it be wanting unity with God is not known, and ſo this is agreeable <hi>to what ſome</hi> have Printed, that without water Baptiſm no ſalvation; and is not this to make another door then Chriſt, and another way then Chriſt? and how much ſhort of this thou haſt endeavoured to make outward water to be (may be eaſily ſeen by the upright in heart) who ſaith, not onely <hi>it muſt continue becauſe fitted to the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:172575:19"/>as Circumciſion was to the Old;</hi> and ſo in like manner as the Teachers of Circumciſion thruſt in that upon the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched <hi>Galatians,</hi> and ſaid except they were Circumciſed they could not be ſaved: do not all you, whoſe judgement this is, do the ſame concerning your water, when you ſay, <hi>It is fitted to the New Teſtament, as Circumciſion was to the Old?</hi> And do not you make Proſelites by your outward water, as they did by Circumciſion? But as if this were not enough, thou ſaiſt, <hi>Outward water is that one Baptiſm ſpoken of by Paul,</hi> joined with the <hi>one Faith, one Lord, and the one God;</hi> as if that outward water either lets into the union with Chriſt, or the want of it makes void the union; and yet you ſay in words, that union with Chriſt muſt precede, and fit the ſubject, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a right can be to water: and yet what it ſhould be that ſhould make you cry up water ſo much I know not (ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you have no poſitive Command by Chriſt in plain words for it) except through the cunning craftineſs of the old ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, who gives leave to cry up, and to reſt upon any thing that is outward, on purpoſe to buſie the mind upon, and to blind the eye from looking at or upon any thing revealed within, that onely can give the knowledge of God in Chriſt, and manifeſts to the Souls its union with, and compleatneſs in Chriſt Jeſus both as to the true Circumciſion and Baptiſm, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11, 12.</p>
            <p>
               <q>The next Queſtion thou ſaiſt, <hi>Thou underſtands not,</hi> which was, whether ſuch do truly diſcern the Lords body, eat his fleſh and drink his blood, who do imagine of the fleſh, blood and bones of Chriſt as the Jews did.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And yet as if thou wert concerned in the Query (though thou underſtand it not, as thou ſaiſt) will return ſome kind of anſwer to it (which is not the part of a wiſe man) to give an anſwer to that which he poſitively ſaith, he <hi>underſtands not,</hi> as thou doſt: but thy anſwer makes it manifeſt, that thou art not ſenſible of that fond imagination, which runs in the minds of filthy creatures, who defile the fleſh; for thou ſaiſt, <hi>If it be meant of the believing Jews, who did believe that Chriſt roſe from the dead with his fleſh and bones as himſelf teſtifies, ſuch may truly diſcern the Lords hody, eat his fleſh and drink his blood,</hi> &amp;c. Doth not this anſwer ſavour of a Jew outward? Or art thou
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:172575:20"/>miſtaken, as thou waſt in thy former quotation? when as there is neither <hi>Chap.</hi> nor <hi>verſ.</hi> to be found; ſo in this alſo ſeeing thou names onely fleſh and bones, and the Query was <hi>fleſh, and blood, and bones,</hi> as a real man hath; or doſt thou imagine of Chriſt that he had or hath fleſh and bones onely, and no blood like a real man? If ſo, ſpeak plainly in thy next Book, that I may know thy Opinion in this particular, and name thy proof; or if it be the Errata of the Printer, let thy next be rectified, that thou hadſt forgotten to put down the blood, and ſo I may paſs it by for the preſent.</p>
            <p>
               <q>To the next Queſtion, which is, whether that fleſh which is meat indeed, and that blood which is drink indeed, be not ſpiritual and that which quickneth and nouriſheth up to eternal life all thoſe that feed thereon?</q>
            </p>
            <p>To this thou confeſſeth, but cannot know it but in the light, no more then the Jews did, who ſaid, how can this man give us his fleſh to eat? And it is as hard a ſaying now, as it was then, though eaſilier confeſt now, becauſe it is written and may be read.</p>
            <p>
               <q>To the laſt Query, which is, What is that fleſh that profiteth nothing? And what is that fleſh after which Chriſt was once known, yet henceforth know we him ſo no more?</q>
            </p>
            <p>To which thou returns this anſwer, <hi>Chriſt in</hi> John 6.63. <hi>ſhews that it is the Spirit that quickneth, and therefore without that all is without profit, whatever is done in the fleſh without the Spirit; and ſo if you take it of being implyed in Ordinances with the fleſh, or outward man onely, it profiteth nothing.</hi> This is thy anſwer to the firſt part of the Query, <hi>viz.</hi> What is that fleſh which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth nothing? Can any wiſe man take this for an anſwer to the Queſtion, or is it not a declining the Queſtion, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering to another Queſtion of thy own framing? As if thou had been asked, whether that worſhip that is performed in the fleſh or outward man onely without the Spirit of God profiteth or not? If this had been the Queſtion, then thou hadſt returned an anſwer ſomewhat pertinent; but the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion that thou was to anſwer to, was, What is that fleſh that profiteth nothing? Conſidering what the foregoing Queſtion was (and thy anſwer to it) <hi>viz.</hi> that there is a fleſh
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:172575:20"/>
               <hi>that is ſpiritual, and doth nouriſh to eternal life all thoſe that feed thereon:</hi> then comes this Queſtion in the next words (as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending upon the foregoing Queſtion) and what then is that fleſh that profiteth nothing, ſeeing there is fleſh that nouriſhes up to eternal life? But thou in ſtead of giving an anſwer, what fleſh it is that profiteth nothing, tells a ſtory of what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is born in the fleſh or outward man, without the Spirit, profits not, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> A Child that reads his Primer, might have ſaid ſo much by rote out of the <hi>Catechiſm;</hi> and yet thou quotes <hi>John</hi> 6.63. as if thy anſwer were intended to that place of Scripture, as if thou didſt believe the Queſtion was grounded upon that place, which anſwer of thine doth manifeſt, as if Chriſt were ſpeaking in this place of worſhipping in the fleſh without the Spirit, and inſtructing his Diſciples that the worſhipping in the fleſh without the Spirit profiteth nothing; which thing (though true in it ſelf) yet not true in this place, as being the thing Chriſt was at this time teaching his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, for he was here rather rectifying, and informing of them aright, ſeeing they ſeemed to be prejudiced at Chriſts foregoing words about eating his fleſh and drinking his blood, and ſaying at the 57. <hi>ver.</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes"> he that eateth me, even he ſhall live by me, and at the 58. <hi>ver.</hi> This is that bread which came down from Heaven: not as your fathers did eat Manna, and are dead: he that eateth of this bread ſhall live for ever; and at the 60. <hi>ver.</hi> Many therefore of his Diſciples, when they heard this, ſaid, This is an hard ſaying, Who can hear it? When Jeſus knew in himſelf that his Diſciples murmured at it, he ſaid unto them, Doth this offend you? What and if ye ſhall ſee the Son of man aſcend up where he was before? It is the Spirit that quickneth, the fleſh profiteth nothing: the words that I ſpeak unto you, they are Spirit, and they are life.</q> So that it is manifeſt Chriſts drift and ſcope in this place is to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie his Diſciples that murmured about his telling them of of eating his fleſh and drinking his blood; and to take them off from looking at his outward fleſhly preſence, as if his outward fleſh, or outward words, were that which they were to feed upon, or alwaies to expect to hear: but there was another fleſh to be known, and other work to be read in the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:172575:21"/>inward man by the Spirit, for that quickneth, and thoſe words are Spirit and life; but the fleſh profiteth nothing: ſo by this may the enlightned underſtanding ſee and read plainly the ſcope and drift of Chriſts Words, and not to be ſpoken in that ſence which thou and others in your vain minds con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive; but have a deeper underſtanding, which the children of light are acquainted withal: ſo that the Query yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains unanſwered (by thee) <hi>viz.</hi> what then is the fleſh that profiteth nothing.</p>
            <p>And for thy anſwer to the ſecond part of the Query, <hi>viz.</hi> and what is that fleſh after which Chriſt was once known, yet henceforth know we him ſo no more: to which thou anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, <hi>To know any man or Chriſt after the fleſh, it was to know ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the natural line of</hi> Abram, <hi>and ſo according to the firſt Covenant; but now know we him no more, that is not by a natural deſcent; but he that is in Chriſt is a new Creature, and all the old things of the firſt Covenant are paſſed away, and all things are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come new:</hi> and thou quotes <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.3, 4, 5. and ſaith, <hi>We will help to clear the ſence of this place,</hi> viz. what is that fleſh after which Chriſt was once known; yet henceforth know we him ſo no more. By this anſwer to the Query, thou haſt but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted thy ignorance of Chriſt after the Spirit; for doth the knowledge of Chriſt after the Spirit teach to deny the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural deſcent of Chriſt after the fleſh, ſeeing it is reckoned up as one of the Iſraelites Priviledges, <hi>viz.</hi> of whom as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the fleſh Chriſt came, who is over all God bleſſed for ever, Amen, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.4, 5. Or is Chriſt changed from what he was? Or is he the ſame yeſterday and to day and for ever? And doth the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> teach to forget the Genealogy of Chriſt from <hi>Abram?</hi> Or hath he forgotten his love to his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and kinſmen according to the fleſh, which he ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.3. he could wiſh himſelf ſeparated from Chriſt for them? Or doth he inſtruſt children after they are come to the knowledge of Chriſt no more to know their Parents after the fleſh or natural deſcent, or any other man after any natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral line? Surely to ſay ſo, had been crime enough againſt the people called <hi>Quakers;</hi> then might thou have had ſome ground to cry out of their diſreſpect to Superiours, and of the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect of children in not obeying their Parents, and ſubjects
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:172575:21"/>in not giving honour to Magiſtrates, and of ſervants in not obeying of their Maſters after the fleſh, which in thy Book thou ſeems to blame the <hi>Quakers</hi> for their remiſneſs therein, and doſt thou do the ſame thing? Or doſt thou go about to interpret <hi>Pauls</hi> words to ſuch a ſence? Whereas he himſelf was ſo far from denying his natural deſcent or linage, or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Priviledge, that upon occaſion he reckons it up again and again, and ſtands upon it, and is not condemned for it: and doth he write to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to know no man after the natural line or deſcent? No not Chriſt himſelf: What doth <hi>Paul</hi> make void <hi>Matthews</hi> and <hi>Lukes</hi> reckoning up of the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral line or deſcent of Chriſt from <hi>Abraham?</hi> Are we no more to know Chriſt ſo? What do the Chriſtians with it in their Bibles then, if Chriſt be no more to be known ſo? But let us ſee if the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> have one word tending that way, in "that place thou quotes, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.16. <q>For he is ſpeaking how the love of Chriſt conſtrained them at the 14. <hi>ver.</hi> and the cauſe of it, becauſe ſaith he we thus judge, that if one died for all, then were all dead: and that he died for all, that they which live ſhould not henceforth live unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but unto him which died for them, and roſe again. Wherefore from henceforth know we no man according to the fleſh (for ſo it is, and ſome tranſlations read it ſo) yea, though we have known Chriſt according to the fleſh, yet now henceforth know we him no more. Therefore if any man be in Chriſt, he is a new creature: old things are paſt away, behold, all things are become new. And all things are of God, who hath reconciled us to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by Jeſus Chriſt, &amp;c.</q> 
               <hi>James Pope,</hi> what ground is here for thy conceived imagination? therefore wait upon the Lord in the light of his Son, that thou may be made alive by God, by being his workmanſhip in Chriſt Jeſus; and then thou wilt know how the word henceforth in the 15. <hi>ver.</hi> anſwers to the word henceforth in the 16. <hi>ver.</hi> and then thou wilt ſee how ſuch inventions and interpretations of thy own brain are ſome of thoſe old things, which then thou wilt behold paſſing away, as thou becomes a new Creation, and all things will be of God; and in that day thou wilt know the firſt Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and its vaniſhing by the new &amp; everlaſting Covenant,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:172575:22"/>which is Gods free gift; but known to none who are alive without the Law, and have their firſt husband living; ſuch muſt know a bitter cup, and a day of death, before ever they can be married to Chriſt. Take this in love to thy Soul <hi>(James Pope)</hi> for this is the Word of the Lord to thee, and is of nearer concernment to thee, then as yet thou art aware of. And for that of <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.3, 4, 5. it proves nothing of thy conceit and invention, but rather may ſerve to condemn thee, who art comparing outward circumciſion and outward waſhing together, as being fitted to the New Teſtament, as outward circumciſion was to the Old: but we are the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion which worſhip God in the Spirit, and have no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in the fleſh, neither Faith in any outward waſhing with outward water: but our Faith ſtands in Chriſt alone, in whom we are compleat, both as to the true Circumciſion, and to the one Baptiſm, and to the one bread in which we have Communion together in the body; and as many as are joyned to the Lord are one Spirit, and are of one heart and one Soul, and do not deny any of the Goſpel Ordinances, or plead for the abrogating of them, as thou ſaiſt the Query ſeems to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: but this we plead againſt, will-worſhip and all like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and dead imitations in the worſhip of God; for by the Goſpel of our Salvation are we made alive, and do not ruſh into Gods ſervice, without fear and the leadings of his Spirit; having in times paſt felt by experience, and ſmarted for having a form of godlineſs, but not ſenſible of the power; and a name to live, and accounted as worſhippers, but were in the death, as many more are at this day who ſay they are alive, and ſay they ſee but are blind; and who required theſe things at your hands will be their anſwer when they think to enter by them or for them: and it is not enough that I have read or heard others did them, but I muſt know whether they are required at my hands, and whether I am appointed by my Lord and Maſter to do them, ſeeing he hath ſeveral appointments for his ſervants, and none are exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from learning of him what to do every day, and knowing <q rend="margQuotes">his voice and following his Counſel, who is faithful to him that made him a high Prieſt, and is worthy of more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour then <hi>Moſes,</hi> inaſmuch as he who builded the Houſe,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:172575:22"/>hath more honour then the Houſe; for every Houſe is buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by ſome, but he that builds all things is God; and <hi>Moſes</hi> verily was faithful in all his Houſe as a ſervant, for Teſtimony of thoſe things which were to be ſpoken after, but Chriſt as a Son over his own houſe, whoſe houſe are we if we hold faſt the confidence, and the rejoycing of the Hope firm to the end: wherefore as the Holy Ghoſt ſaith, to day if ye will hear his voice harden not your hearts, &amp;c.</q> So by this thou maiſt underſtand what Houſe it is that Chriſt is a faithful high Prieſt over, and gives Laws and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did to the outward people of the Jews, and Chriſt doth to the inward Jews, who is a Prophet like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and is now to be heard, for by him God ſpeaks, and whoever hears not him ſhall be cut off from among the people; and ſuch a one who hears not his voice immediately, is but a Jew outward, though in the practice of all thoſe outward waſhings and other outward things done by the Saints, and recorded in the Scripture, whoſe praiſe is of men, and as yet Chriſt is not come to him the ſecond time without ſin to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and therefore knows him not to be the end of all things, and to put an end to ſin, and to finiſh tranſgreſſion, and to bring in everlaſting righteouſneſs, in whom we are compleat, who is the head of all principalities and powers.</p>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Now follows an Anſwer to thy Queries.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Q. <hi>WHether it is not a high degree of pride and arrogancy, for any to go about to exalt their own wiſdom above the wiſdom of Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yea, and ſo do all thoſe who are wiſe above what is written, and pry into things which they have not ſeen, and ſo become puffed up in their fleſhly minds, boaſting of other mens lines, haſtning to be rich, but will not wait upon the Lord to receive the true riches from him, which are his gifts, nor the true wiſdom from him, which is not taught by the precepts and cuſtoms of men, but comes down from above, and is firſt pure and peaceable, and eaſie to be intreated.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Q. <hi>Whether they do not ſo, that account thoſe Ordinances which
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:172575:23"/>he hath appointed too low and carnal for them to ſubmit unto, not mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that this fooliſhneſs of God is wiſer then men?</hi> 1 Cor. 1.15.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> All thoſe who deſpiſe or account the Ordinances (which Chriſt hath appointed them to ſubmit unto and walk in the practiſe of) too low and carnal, do ſet up and exalt their own wiſdoms above the Wiſdom of God: and of this ſort are they who neglect the means which God hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto eternal life, which is to wait upon and ſtand ſtill in the light and grace of God which appears to manifeſt Gods Mind and Will unto every man and woman, that ſo they may know it &amp; do it in obedience to his requiring of it at their hands; that ſo they may not fall under that righteous cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Lord, ſaying to ſome, <hi>Who hath required theſe things at your hands?</hi> though performed (in times paſt) by the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Lord, and by him required at their hands: and yet others may be condemned for doing the ſame things, the Lord forbidding all likeneſſes to be made, whether of things in Heaven or things in Earth, &amp;c. And for thy quotation of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.15. I know not what thou intends by it, except to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt how thy mind is troubled for Baptizing in thy own name; for in that place <hi>Paul</hi> thanks God that he had Baptized but a few, leaſt any ſhould have thought ſo of him, intimating that thoſe who Baptize many, or lay ſo much ſtreſs upon it, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelves to be guilty of this charge: but it may be an Errata of the Printer, and ſo I ſhall paſs it by.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Q. <hi>Whether thoſe who deny the continuance of water Baptiſm which Chriſt Commanded, and his ſervants faithfully practiſed after his Reſurrection, in memorial thereof, are willing the doctrine of the Reſurrection of the body of Chriſt as the firſt fruits of the Reſurrection of the bodies of the Saints ſhould be perpetuated?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thoſe who deny the continuance of water Baptiſm, or any other thing, which Chriſt hath Commanded them to obſerve and continue, are tranſgreſſors; and thoſe are no leſs, who continue it in their own wills and imitation onely, the Lord not requiring it at their hands, he being a Spirit, and will be worſhipped in Spirit, and by the Spirit, and not becauſe <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was the place of worſhip, therefore ſtill to continue: no more are men ſtill to go down into outward water, becauſe ſome were commanded ſo to do, except they
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:172575:23"/>know the Lord requires it at their hands, by the moving and ſtirring of the Spirit of God in their own hearts and breſts, which thing they do and ſhould have done, had they never read or heard of any ſuch thing done by any before them: and he that thus goeth into the water, or doth any other thing, worſhips God aright, and finds not out his worſhip himſelf; but he himſelf is firſt ſought out of God to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God in the Spirit, for God is a Spirit, and ſuch God on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeeks to worſhip him, though many others otherwiſe ſeeks to worſhip God; but he will not accept an offering at their hand, which cauſes many to be filled with wrath againſt thoſe at whoſe hands the Lord doth accept an offering, becauſe they do it in the Spirit of Faith, and ſuch do not deny the one of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering that perfects for ever them that are ſanctified, nor the memorial of the Reſurrection of the body of Chriſt, nor the Reſurrection of the bodies of the Saints; but do equally condemn the folly both of thoſe who ſay there is no Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the dead, and who yet are to ſeek what the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the body is, and who ſay how are the dead raiſed up, and with what body do they come: to them both I ſay as the Apoſtle ſaid, Thou fool, that which thou ſoweſt is not quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, except it die; and he that hath not part in the firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, for all his ſhews, memorials and figures, ſhall not eſcape the ſecond death; but he that knows he hath part in the firſt Reſurrection, over him the ſecond death ſhall have no power; and he is willing that the doctrine of the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the body of Chriſt, as the firſt fruits of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the bodies of the Saints ſhould be perpetuated, though ſome ſay now of ſuch, as once was ſaid of <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 17. that he was a ſetter forth of ſtrange gods, becauſe he Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto them Jeſus and the Reſurrection, and this query doth not altogether excuſe the Author from that ſpirit; but <hi>James,</hi> here is three things for thee to prove by plain Scripture and not by thy conſequences, leaſt thou be guilty of that which you of your way have charged upon the Prieſts. 1. To prove Chriſt commanded water baptiſm ſince his Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. 2. To prove that his ſervants practiced it by vertue of that command after his Reſurrection. 3. That he commanded outward waſhing to be practiced after his Reſurrection in
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:172575:24"/>memorial of his Reſurrection, and that the practitioners did it ſo accordingly; all which thou ſeems to affirm in thy query, and to take it for granted, and then a more particular anſwer to them all thou mayeſt receive according to the Scripture of Truth.</p>
               <p>Q. 4. <hi>Whether thoſe that deny the Ordinance of breaking bread, as it was inſtituted by Chriſt, and practiced by his Primitive Saints, are willing the memorial of Chriſts death and blood-ſhed ſhould remain among his Saints until his next coming?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thoſe who deny any Ordinance or inſtitution of Chriſt to thoſe of whom he required it, and to that end for which he appointed it, as the cauſe of his requiring it at their hands, are tranſgreſſors, and are not willing that the end or cauſe of his commanding it ſhould be fulfilled or accompliſhed, nor do not wait or look for his appearing the ſecond time without ſin unto ſalvation, but believe they are ſaved though they commit ſin, and believe that freedom from all ſin they can never attain while living in this viſible world, and ſuch are not onely unwilling that the memorial of Chriſts death and blood-ſhed ſhould remain among his Saints, but are both ignorant and unbelieving, that the blood of Jeſus Chriſt cleanſes all that know it and believe in it from all unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and preſents them perfect unto God without ſpot or wrinkle or any ſuch thing, and ſuch onely (as thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve) celebrate the memorial of Chriſts death and blood-ſhed, as are dead with Chriſt, and ſuch are free from ſin, and ſuch though they neither eat bread nor drink wine, but feed upon locuſt and wild hony, or are content with a dinner of green herbs, ſuch I ſay do truely ſhew forth the Lords death in their conformity to it, and his blood ſhed in that their hearts are ſprinkled from an evil conſcience to ſerve the living God in truth and righteouſneſs.</p>
               <p>Q. 5. <hi>Whether thoſe that ſay that Scripture,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.26. <hi>is meant of Chriſts coming in Spirit, do not in effect ſay that the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of breaking of bread was appointed for unbelievers to eat and drink damnation, till Chriſt come to them in Spirit?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Was it not in the ſame night in which he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed, that he took bread? and is not Chriſt a ſpirit, and his coming in ſpirit? or doth he come out of the ſpirit, or is there
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:172575:24"/>a coming of Chriſt, and not in the ſpirit? is Chriſt and the ſpirit divided, or can he come and he not in the ſpirit, and the ſpirit in him? and where Chriſt is preſent, is not the ſpirit there alſo, and he in it, and it in him, and yet but one? And doth it at all follow in ſound judgement or good underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that <hi>they who ſay the</hi> 1 Cor. 11.26. <hi>is meant of Chriſts coming in ſpirit, muſt needs or in effect ſay that the Ordinance of breaking bread was appointed for unbelievers to eat and drink damnation till Chriſt come to them in ſpirit,</hi> any more then it follows that the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples had no power at all, becauſe they were commanded to wait at Jeruſalem for the promiſe of the Father, and that they ſhould receive power after the Holy Ghoſt was come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.4.8. <hi>ver.</hi> or any more then it may be ſaid of Chriſt that his words implyed, or that he in effect ſaid that his Diſciples had not his ſpirit at all in them (and ſo were none of his) when he ſaid to them (in theſe words) <hi>how much more ſhall your heavenly Father give the Holy ſpirit to them that ask him? Luke</hi> 11.13. and yet all that time God was their Father, and they could not ask aright without the ſpirit, and yet Chriſt ſaith, <hi>how much more ſhall your heavenly Father give the holy ſpirit to them that ask him?</hi> ſo do they (who ſay that the coming of Chriſt in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. is his coming in ſpirit) in effect ſay any more or otherwiſe, that thoſe had not the ſpirit at all, or were unbelievers, to whom Chriſt ſaid, <hi>take, eat, this is my body which is broken for you,</hi> &amp;c. becauſe they were to wait for a further and fuller manifeſtation of him in them; and he went away in that fleſhly appearance, that he might come again unto them, and abide with them for ever, and this Chriſt prayed for and performed accordingly, John 17.23. <hi>I in them, and thou in me, that they may be made perfect in one,</hi> &amp;c. ſo that to ſay (till he come) is meant of Chriſts coming in ſpirit, doth no more deny or in effect ſay that the breaking of bread was appointed for unbelievers to eat and drink damnation, &amp;c. then Chriſt in ſaying (the Father would give his holy Spirit to them that ask him) in effect ſaid that God would give his holy Spirit to them that asked or prayed without the Spirit, or then Chriſt in effect ſaid, that they who waited in their wills, and in the form without the power, ſhould receive power after the Holy Ghoſt was come upon them, or then in
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:172575:25"/>effect Chriſt ſhould ſay, they had not the holy Spirit at all as yet, becauſe it was to come upon them, and ſo (till he come) though meant of his coming in Spirit, yet doth not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, but thoſe to whom Chriſt ſpake had a meaſure of his Spirit already come to them, and was in them, and ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them not to eat and drink damnation; but by eating of that bread, and drinking of that cup, they were to ſhew the Lords death till he come, and then when he was come, who was ſhewed by that eating and drinking, the ſhew needed no longer, the thing ſhewed being come and witneſſed, the bread indeed and drink indeed was known, and Eternal life inherited.</p>
               <p>Q. 6. <hi>Whether it is not granted by thoſe that ſeem to deny it, that the forecited place directs the Church at</hi> Corinth <hi>to the uſe of an Ordinance, ſeeing ſome might eat this bread and drink this cup, which is alſo called fleſh and blood, unworthily, but thoſe that eat truly that fleſh that is meat indeed, and drink that blood which is drink indeed, are nouriſhed up to Eternal life, ſo that while ſome do eat and drink in that Ordinance unworthily, and ſo eat and drink damnation, others by faith feed upon the benefits of Chriſts death and blood-ſhed, and ſo are nouriſhed up to Eternal life?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Is there any thing in the fore-cited place, that directs to the uſe of (that which thou cals) an Ordinance, ſurely in this, thy zeal out-runs thy underſtanding, ſeeing thoſe be the words of the fore-cited place, <hi>viz. for as often as ye eat this bread, and drink this cup, ſhew ye the Lords death till he come</hi> (for ſo it is on the Margent) <hi>ſhew ye;</hi> what is here of direction in theſe words, as to the uſe of an Ordinance, as thou ſayeſt (let the wiſe in heart judge) but doth not the Apoſtles words, aſmuch, if not more ſignifie to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> that they might forbear their eating and drinking in that wiſe as they did eat and drink, and their unworthineſs was, in not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning of the Lords body, and for that cauſe was many ſick and weak, &amp;c. and for that diſorder which was amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the Apoſtle reproves them, as for their greedineſs and drunkenneſs, &amp; the like; and exhorts them to eat at home in their own houſes, but he never calls it an Ordinance to be miniſtred once a Moneth, or once a week, and that alwayes, by ſome men or man appointed by the reſt in their wills and wayes, ſome to buy wine and bread, and others to break it,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:172575:25"/>and deliver to the reſt; but Chriſt did not do ſo, <hi>for in the ſame night in which he was betrayed he took bread, and when he had given thanks he brake it, and ſaid, take, eat, this is my body, this do in remembrance of me; after the ſame manner alſo he took the cup, when he had Supped,</hi> and did he bid you do ſo, or do you do ſo after Supper? or can you give thanks as he did? or do you know what he ſaid when he gave thanks? or do you imitate him in ſaying his very words in one thing, <hi>viz.</hi> (this is my body) and do you ſpeak your own words in other things, as when you give thanks? or do you take a piece of bread and a cup of wine, and ſay nothing at all, but eat and drink? and if you do it not in the ſame manner, which he did it in, is it then his Ordinance, or your invention, ſeeing Gods Ordinances muſt be kept as they were delivered, and obſerved as he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them, otherwiſe they are none of his; and if not his, then but a likeneſs, and if a likeneſs, then that which God hath forbidden, and ſo is Idolatry, and he an Idolator that ſo worſhips, and in that ſtate cannot enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God. And whereas thou ſayeſt, <hi>ſome might eat this bread and drink this cup, which is alſo called fleſh and blood, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take heed <hi>(James)</hi> of calling a lie, <hi>a plea for truth, in love to truth,</hi> remember the Title of thy book, where is that bread and that cup, which a man may eat unworthily, called fleſh and blood, as thou poſitively affirms in thy query it is; ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thou diſcerns not Chriſts body, for if thou did, thou wouldſt learn to ſpeak truth; are not theſe the words of the Apoſtle (that thou intendſt) <hi>viz. wherefore whoſoever ſhall eat this bread and drink this cup of the Lord unworthily, ſhall be guilty of the body and blood of the Lord:</hi> but where is it called fleſh and blood? ſurely this is a groſs errour of thine, not onely to call the outward bread, &amp; the outward cup (which an unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and wicked man may eat and drink) <hi>fleſh and blood,</hi> and if <hi>fleſh and blood,</hi> whoſe <hi>fleſh and blood?</hi> is it not <hi>Chriſts fleſh, and Chriſts blood?</hi> and can an unworthy man and woman eat and drink that? ſurely no, if Chriſts words be true, and I muſt believe him before thee <hi>(James)</hi> and he ſaith, <hi>John</hi> 6.54. <hi>whoſoever eateth my fleſh and drinketh my blood hath Eternal life,</hi> how ſayeſt thou then in thy query, ſome might eat this bread, and drink this cup, which (thou ſayeſt) is alſo called <hi>fleſh and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:172575:26"/>blood, unworthily?</hi> but where is the bread &amp; the cup (which ſome may eat and drink unworthily) called <hi>fleſh and blood?</hi> take heed of ſlandering the Scripture. And then thou draweſt up thy query into a ſhort concluſion in theſe words, <hi>viz. ſo that while ſome do eat and drink in that Ordinance unworthily, and ſo eat and drink damnation, other by faith feed upon the benefits of Chriſts death and blood-ſhed, and ſo are nouriſhed up to Eternal life,</hi> and herein thou haſt made a good confeſſion, that while ſome in that which thou calls an Ordinance eat and drink damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, others who live <hi>by faith and feed upon the benefits of Chriſts death and blood-ſhed</hi> (and are not that which thou calls an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance) and yet are nouriſhed up to Eternal life, and ſo of what thou haſt ſpoken this is the ſum, that ſome in that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance eat and drink damnation, and others out of it, feed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the living bread that comes down from heaven, and have Eternal life abiding in them.</p>
               <p>Q. 7. <hi>Whether thoſe that deny Church fellowſhip, do not forſake their own mercies, ſeeing Gods children have found by ſweet experience that it is of ſingular uſe for their building upon their moſt holy faith, it being the place of Chriſts promiſed preſence, where he hath command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the bleſſing and life for evermore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thoſe that deny that Church that is in God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. and that fellowſhip that is in the light, as he is in the light, 1 <hi>John <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> denyes the true Church-fellowſhip, and forſakes their own mercies, and that light in which alone all the Saints ever had all their ſweet experiences given them of Gods love, and tender mercy to them, and in that who ever walked, and continued in it, built up one another in their moſt holy faith, that being the place of Chriſts promiſed preſence; for there he dwells for ever, and out of his light none can meet with him, or know him; and out of that is the falſe Church and Church-fellowſhip, and Chriſtian outward, and baptiſm outward, that onely waſhes away the filth of the fleſh, but knows not the anſwer of a good conſcience by the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt, for from the true light was and is the falſe Church and fellowſhip, <hi>for they went out from us,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, who had his fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in the light.</p>
               <p>Q. 8. <hi>Whether they may not moſt truely be ſaid to live above
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:172575:26"/>Ordinances, that faithfully wait upon, and live to Chriſt in the uſe of them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> They that wait upon and live to Chriſt in the uſe of Ordinances, cannot be ſaid to live above them; for that which God hath appointed and Ordained, as the way to Eternal life and happineſs, none may live above it; for the the way and the life are one, and he that is in the way, is in the truth, and in the life alſo; and none can be in the truth and (moſt truely) live above the way ordained of God to life; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can any live above the way, and yet be in the truth; and therefore thy query is an unlearned queſtion, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſts thy ignorance of the myſteries of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Q. 9. <hi>Whether if thoſe who deſpiſed Moſes Law died without mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy under two or three witneſſes, ought not thoſe then, that (either in word, practice or writing) deſpiſe Chriſts Law, to be deeply humbled and truely repent of ſo grievous a ſin, eſpecially if they have taught others ſo do?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I hope that is not the Engliſh of thy query, <hi>viz.</hi> that thou wouldſt have them more ſorely puniſhed that deny your water waſhing, then thoſe were that deſpiſed <hi>Moſes</hi> Law. Thoſe who deſpiſe Chriſts Law ought to be deeply humbled, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of it, and turn from it, or they cannot be ſaved; and ſuch are all thoſe who deſpiſe the true light, with which every man that cometh into the world is lighted, and call it natural: for Chriſt is a Law-giver, and gives Laws to his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and his Laws and Ordinances are onely known, and read in the true light, and he which oppoſes or gain-ſays either in himſelf or others the manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Spirit, which is given to every man to profit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, is an unprofitable ſervant unto God, though he be found in all the outward practices of the true Church, for God is a Spirit, and they which worſhip him aright, muſt worſhip in the Spirit, and in the truth, for ſuch God did ſeek to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him in the dayes of the Apoſtles, and ſuch God is ſeeking again, and all others ſhall be diſcovered, and caſt out as dung upon the face of the earth, and ſuch deſpiſers ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold and wonder, and by their mocking at the true light, which lighteth every man that cometh into the world; ſhall their bonds become ſtrong, and their puniſhment become
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:172575:27"/>ſorer then thoſe who deſpiſed <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, if they ſpeedily repent not.</p>
               <p n="10">10 Q. <hi>Whether it will be a good Plea at the dreadful day of Chriſt, to ſay, Lord we would not have deſpiſed thy Laws, if thou hadſt made them to our minds, and we had thought they had been ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual enough?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It will be no good Plea at the dreadful day of Chriſt, neither is it now, to ſay, Lord we would not have deſpiſed thy Laws, if thou hadſt made them to our minds, and we had thought they had been ſpiritual enough: and of this ſort are all thoſe, who put the day of the Lord afar off, and are of the night, and know not the day of the Lord as yet to be dawned, nor the day-ſtar to be riſen in their hearts, but though they draw near with their lips, their hearts are far from God, and their minds are eſtranged from him by wicked works, though in words they confeſs him, yet they are but in their thoughts, and think they ſtand ſure; but their foundation is rottenneſs and built upon the ſands, like all thoſe who ſay and do not, and hear his words but obey them not, and cry, the Temple of the Lord, and Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellowſhip, and Ordinances, but hate to be Reformed, and to have their converſation ordered aright; and ſo cannot ſee Gods Salvation, while they account that too low and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, or legal and natural, which checks and reproves for ſin in the Conſcience, and accuſes for evil, and excuſes when they do well, and reject it and ſlight it as not ſpiritual e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough; and ſuch are they thy Query ſpeaks of; had they known that the light in their Conſciences had been ſpiritual, and that which came from Chriſt the light of the world, and given them to lead out of darkneſs, and that with which they muſt come to ſee themſelves loſt and undone (if ever they be ſaved) and in the ſight and ſence of their miſerable eſtate, to wait for a Saviour, and in that light to ſee him revealed, to ſave when none can help or deliver: I ſay this is the man and the woman, that in truth thy Query ſpeaks of, that ſhall ſay, Lord we would not have deſpiſed thy Laws, if thou hadſt made them to our minds, or if they had been ſpiritual enough: but the light in the Conſcience we liked not, becauſe it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes bore a witneſs for God, againſt all our evil wayes; and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:172575:27"/>now we marvel not that every one that doth evil hates it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it reproves them all; but outward Obſervances and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily Exerciſes we like well, and in theſe Obſervations we look for the Kingdom of Heaven to come: but to give up to be guided by the light in our Conſciences and ſhines in our hearts for that to give us the knowledge of God in the face of Chriſt, we like not; but accounted it not ſufficient to lead to Chriſt, and that which prejudiced us the more againſt the light which ſhines in our hearts (and hath long ſhewed us our evil words before we ſpake them, and our thoughts when they firſt did ariſe in us, before we conſented to them, to follow them) was becauſe we accounted it common to all men, and that which every man had, and that though it ſhewed ſome ſins againſt the Law, yet not all ſins againſt the Goſpel, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief, and therefore ſlighted it as legal and natural; and when it troubled us or reproved us, when we had been wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of thee, O Lord, (as we thought) in breaking bread and drinking wine, and preaching and praying, and the like, which we verily believed had been thy ordinances and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments: and when we were troubled in our ſpirits and minds after ſuch exerciſes as theſe, we looked upon it as the temptation of the Devil, and did not know it to be Gods witneſs in our Conſciences, or his Spirit ſtriving with us, to bring us to ſilence, that ſo we might know the dumb to ſpeak, and the Spirit of the Lord to move, and ſtir and guide in us, and we in all things to be led by it, and ſo in all we did feel Gods acceptance by the Teſtimony of his Spirit in us, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Spirit it ſelf bearing witneſſe with our ſpirits, that we were Gods Children, and the Spirit of truth to lead us into all truth, that ſo by it we might witneſs freedom from the inward troubles of our minds and ſpirits, and the accuſings of Gods witneſs in our Conſciences; and ſo be made free and perfect as pertaining to the Conſcience, by the blood of Chriſt, which is onely known and felt in his light, as the Scripture ſaith, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.7. <hi>If we walk in the light, as he is in the light, we have fellowſhip one with another, and the blood of Jeſus Chriſt his Son cleanſeth us from all ſin.</hi> But we looked on that of God in our Conſciences to be too low, and of the reliques of the old <hi>Adam,</hi> or ſomething of the Law; but we looked upon
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:172575:28"/>our ſelves, as not being under the Law but under grace, and ſo judged our ſelves in Chriſt; and when we were at any time troubled in our Conſciences, we preſently called ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe or other to mind in the Scripture, or thought of ſome comfortable Text, and ſo ſlighted the light in our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, as not to be heeded or regarded, as to receive and witneſs Juſtification from all ſin and trouble in and by it; but looked upon our ſelves as Elected in Chriſt before the world, and that we had known a time when he called us by his Grace (in the uſe of Ordinances) and ſpake peace to us afterward by his Spirit in the Scripture, applying ſome Promiſe to us, and having learned and known theſe things, we believe we can never fall totally; for once in Chriſt and ever in Chriſt, and the Elect cannot be deceived, and we believe our ſelves Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and Juſtified by Chriſt without us, before we had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted one ſin in our own perſons: for Juſtification is but one intire act, and is perfect; but our Sanctification is gradual and imperfect, and Salvation is not works, leaſt any man ſhould boaſt, but of grace freely; and ſo we never mind much what is in us, we know there is enough in Chriſt: and for our ſins they cannot ſeparate us from the love of God in Chriſt Jeſus; and our holineſs or righteouſneſs (though we be never ſo ſtrict) commends us not to God; for if we be Elected, our ſins ſhall not deſtroy or damne us, and if we be reprobated by God, our righteouſneſs or ſtrictneſs in holineſs cannot help us or ſave us: and ſo all our comfort is in a Chriſt without us, and in what he hath done for us already; but for any thing in us that is ſpiritual, or for Chriſt to be in us formed there, and to dwell and inhabit there, and we to feel him and know his voice, and to be ſilent until he ſpeak in us, and to be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by his Spirit in us, and for him to work all our works in us and for us, and we to be juſtified by him who works in us, and not for our works, is that which we looked upon as legal and dangerous, to be led, and guided, and juſtified, and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by Chriſt in us, the Hope of all our Glory, this we thought not ſpiritual enough, nor our carnal minds liked not to have all within; but rather to have ſin within and Chriſt without, and luſts within but righteouſneſs without, and Hell within but Heaven without, and vanity and filthineſs preſent, but
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:172575:28"/>happineſs and bleſſedneſs to come hereafter: but the light which ſhined in our hearts, and lets us ſee the thoughts and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents thereof we believed not in, for that to give us the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the light of the Glory of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt; but looked to get knowledge faſter then that would give us it, and ſurer then the knowledge that came that way, by our running to the Scriptures and other good books, by reading of them, and by ſetting ourſelves to obſerve what we read there, looking upon the Scriptures to be the foundation of Faith and the rule of Life, and what we get out there we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count true knowledge, and by reading of that we can be rich quickly, and wiſe to diſpute, and to anſwer gain-ſayers, and our building is according to that, and built upon that foundation; but for the light that ſhines in our hearts, to wait upon God in that, to be taught by him, and to hear his voice, and to ſee his ſhape, is a tedious, painful, flow and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain way of getting knowledge, and that which hath no delight in it, but is a narrow way and a ſtrait gate to walk in and enter by, and takes up the whole minds of thoſe that are guided by it and walk in it, that they can mind nothing elſe, and makes them ſuch fools, that all wiſe men ſcoff at them, to ſee how they walk up and down as if they cared for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and were grown ſtrangers to the world, and had no fellowſhip with it, but kept out of all its cuſtoms, and wayes, and faſhions, as if they were redeemed out of it (while they walk up and down in it) but this way we like not, but rather a zeal for outward Ordinances and outward Obſervances, and to be ſomewhat ſtrict in them we like pritty well; ſo that we may be kept in our wiſdoms and underſtandings which are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, and not have them confounded nor brought to nothing; but ſtill remain in that nature in which we can live at eaſe in the fleſh, and have felowſhip with the world, and conform to their cuſtoms, and be made partakers of their honours, and flattering titles, and have our thoughts at liberty, and our tongues our own; and this Religion we like well: but for to have all within like thoſe fooliſh bewitched people (called <hi>Quakers</hi>) we like not, and for their wayes, had we thought them to have been ſpiritual enough, and conformable enough to the Scriptures of truth, we would not have deſpiſed
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:172575:29"/>them: but we account them fools for being ſo ſtrict, and our ſelves wiſe for taking our eaſe and pleaſure while we may have it, and yet go to Heaven when we dye, before them; and for to enjoy any great matter in our hearts in this life, we look not for it, if we can but keep our Conſciences quiet it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for us; when the Meſſias comes which is called Chriſt, he will tell us all things, and we look for his perſonal coming, and then it ſhall be glorious times, then we ſhall known all things. And ſo by what I have ſaid, thou maiſt know an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to thy Query, and alſo to that which thou ſaiſt may ſeem a digreſſion, but craves to be favoured in it: onely to thy laſt words of Exhortation (in which thou exhorts, <hi>all to hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the voice of Chriſt in the Goſpel in this day of Grace,</hi> &amp;c. I have this to ſay, Chriſts voice is not heard but in the light, nor the Goſpel is not known but in the light, though <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew, Mark, Luke</hi> and <hi>John</hi>'s writings may be read and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred by him or them that are in darkneſs, and yet the Goſpel hid; and here they may be loſt, becauſe their minds are blinded in them by the god of this world, who hath the glory of this world to give unto men, that ſo he might keep the eye of their minds ſhut, leaſt with it they ſhould ſee the light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt the Image of God, and it ſhould ſhine into them, and they be converted, and then the Goſpel which once was hid becomes the Goſpel of their Salvation, and Chriſt Gods Image ſuch comes to know and bear in the world, and ſuch <hi>Preach not themſelves, but Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus the Lord, and themſelves ſervants for Jeſus ſake: for God who commanded light to ſhine out of darkneſs, hath ſhined into their hearts, to give them the light of the knowledge of the glory of God in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.4, 5, 6. And ſuch know how they come by their knowledge, for the light gave it them, and they are not vain talkers, nor boaſts not in other mens lines, but keep to their own meaſure of Grace, and boaſts not about it, but knows it and keeps in it; for there onely is ſafety, and condemnation is avoided, and juſtification is enjoyed, and ſuch are ever with the Lord, and from him cannot be ſeparated, becauſe in his Son (that is Truth) and in that underſtanding which is Gods gift, in which alone Peace, Juſtification and Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation with God through him is witneſſed and life Eternal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herited
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:172575:29"/>for evermore, which all that are out of the light) (with which they are lighted, though never ſo much puffed up with knowledge) are ignorant of, and ſtrangers to the life and immortality that is brought to light by the Goſpel, in which Goſpel they hear Chriſts voice, and knows it from the voice of a ſtranger, both within them and without them, and through the annointing within them they know all things, and need no man to teach them, but as the ſame an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing teacheth them, which is truth and no lye; and ſuch cannot be ſeduced, becauſe of the annointing which they have received, whereby they ſavour and try the ſpirits whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be of God or no, for every ſpirit that confeſſeth not that Jeſus Chriſt is come in their fleſh, is not of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="queries">
               <head>Here follows ſome Queries for <hi>James Pope,</hi> or ſome others to anſwer in Gods fear, and with plainneſs of ſpeech, that ſo all that reads may be edified by his or their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, and Scripture proofs produced to witneſs the ſame.</head>
               <p n="1">1. WHat is the firſt Principle of the pure Religion, is it ſomething within man, or ſomething without man?</p>
               <p n="2">2. What is the Foundation of Faith and Rule of Life to all that are or ſhall be ſaved, is it ſomething within or ſomething without, ſomething created, or ſomething not made but E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whether do <hi>Abrams</hi> Children now follow his ſteps in making that the Rule of their Life, and Foundation of their Faith, which was the Rule and Foundation of his Life, and whether that Goſpel which is the Goſpel of their Salvation now, was not the Goſpel of his Salvation, and preached to him then in his day?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whether that be not a fundamental Principle in Chriſts Religion which a man muſt know and take up daily, or he cannot be one of Chriſts Diſciples, and whether the Croſs of Chriſt be not ſuch a fundamental, if it be, what is it, and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:172575:30"/>where is it, that every one that deſires to learn of Chriſt may know it and take it up daily?</p>
               <p n="5">5. Whether to ſtand ſtill is not a fundamental in Chriſts Religion, ſeeing every ones ſtrength is in it, and Salvation cannot be ſeen but by it, nor ſafety witneſſed but through it; if it be ſuch a fundamental, what is it, and how may the ignorant be inſtructed in the knowledge of it? deſcribe it plainly.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Whether that is not a fundamental in the true Religion, which if a man know not and be not partaker of, he hath no life in him; but if he do know and be partaker of, he hath life Eternal: &amp; whether the fleſh and blood of Chriſt be not ſuch a fundamental, ſeeing Chriſt faith, <hi>Except you eat the fleſh of the Son of man, and drink his blood, you have no life in you;</hi> and again, <hi>Whoſoever eateth my fleſh and drinketh my blood hath Eternal Life?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Whether the Tree of knowledge of good and evil, be in theſe dayes, if it be, what is it now, and where doth it grow, and whether it be ſtill forbidden to be fed upon or ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of, and when doth a man eat of it; and what is that death which a man dies, when he eats of it?</p>
               <p n="8">8. What is the Tree of Life, which they who keep the Commandements of God have right to eat of, and what is that Paradice of God where it grows, and what is it to eat of it?</p>
               <p n="9">9. Whether he that doth not diſcern the Lords body daily in his ordinary eating and drinking, doth not eat and drink damnation, ſeeing not diſcerning the body is the cauſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, or whether is the Lords body diſcerned by ſome once or twice a year, and other ſome once a moneth, and others (it may be) once a week, and ſome never, if ſo be that breaking of outward bread, and drinking of outward wine in ſuch a way (as ſome call a Sacrament, and others the Ordinance of break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bread) be that alone wherein the Lords body is diſeerned and fed upon?</p>
               <p n="10">10 Whether waſhing of the body with outward water be neceſſary to ſalvation, or that a man which is not ſo waſhed, cannot be ſaved (if he cannot) whether you do not make two doors to enter into life (if he may) then whether he that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in by Chriſt the door, is not compleat in his entrance
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:172575:30"/>(and in Chriſt his life) as well in being truely baptized, as Circumciſed, ſeeing the Apoſtle ſaith the Saints <hi>were compleat in Chriſt, in whom they were Circumciſed with the Circumciſion made without hands, and buried with him in Baptiſm wherein they were riſen with him through the faith of the operation of God,</hi> Col. 2.10, 11, 12.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Whether he that baptizes now (with outward water) muſt not manifeſt his Commiſſion thereunto, either by the ſame Authority that they did, or by ſomething of equal power thereunto, ſeeing he that baptized with water was greater then all the Prophets, and was ſent by God to do it, but ſaw the end for which it was appointed, for he that ſent him to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize with water, ſaid unto him, <hi>upon whom thou ſhalt ſee the Spirit deſcending and remaining on him, the ſame is he which bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizeth with the Holy Ghoſt; and I ſaw and bear record that this is the Son of God, Joh.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.33.34.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Whether Baptiſm with water was not in its full force, before <hi>Mat.</hi> 28 if yea (and water Baptiſm was ſtill to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued) why might not Chriſts Diſciples have followed <hi>Johns</hi> example, without any new command to them, as well as you follow their example (as you ſay) without another, or new command to you, ſeeing it is written, <hi>John</hi> was a man ſent from God to Baptize with water, &amp;c. or may it not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded (from the ſame reaſon) that the Baptiſm of the Spirit was and is intended, ſeeing water is not at all expreſſed in <hi>Mat</hi> 28 nor <hi>Mark</hi> 16. but rather the contrary, for it is ſuch a waſhing as is neceſſary to ſalvation.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Whether the falſe Church or Apoſtacy conſiſts ſo much in the ceſſation or declenſion from outward obſervances (ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time practiced by the ſervants of God) or rather in their keeping up, or imitating of thoſe outward practices in their own wills, out of the ſame life and power by which they were once required and performed, by thoſe of whom they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, ſeeing it is a charge both againſt the Jewiſh Church (in that they drew near with their lips, and multiplyed ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and were not charged for neglect of outwards, but for reſiſting of the Holy Ghoſt, as their fathers had done) and in the Apoſtle dayes, was it the want of the form, or
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:172575:31"/>men having a form (and denying the power) that made the times perilous?</p>
               <p n="14">14. Whether that coming of Chriſt ſpoken of in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.7. which ſome of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> were <hi>waiting for</hi> (which coming of Chriſt the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>ſhould confirm them to the end</hi> (or were the <hi>Corinthians</hi> never confirmed) and that coming ſpoken of in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5. (which coming is ſaid <hi>to manifeſt the counſels of the heart,</hi> &amp;c.) was not the coming ſpoken of in the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til which they were to do ſo and ſo, ſeeing the former coming was a coming not yet obtained, but they were waiting for it, &amp;c. and whether ſome amongſt the <hi>Corinthians</hi> did not wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the coming of the Lord as aforeſaid?</p>
               <p n="15">15. Whether the ſervants of the Lord now, may not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden (by the holy Ghoſt) to do ſome things now (once done by the Saints) as <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> were forbidden to Preach the Goſpel in <hi>Aſia, Acts</hi> 16.6. (though by Chriſts general Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, they were to Preach the Goſpel to all Nations) and be juſtified by the Lord in their ſo doing (as <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> was) while others run on in imitation, and are condemned by the Spirit in themſelves, the Lord not requiring them at their hands?</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
